more than just daily tasks. Anytime we invite Christ into anything that we do, we see how we allow
him to work through us. People are seeking the love of Christ and Christ wants to allow us to be a
vessel to share his love with whoever comes to our door.
calls our phone, with whoever we're cooking with, or cooking for, whoever we
encounter at the grocery store, any aspect of our daily life that involves
just the day-to-day things we must do can be an opportunity for us to invite
Christ into those practices. And so we've kind of...
been exploring this concept through this podcast and even the last one, where daily things don't
need to just be boxed, like now it's time to work, now it's time to rest, now it's time to clean,
now it's time to cook. Yes, these things need to have their proper time and be planned out,
but Christ can be a part of all of them. So it's not as if Christ is only a part of our life when
We're attending the Divine Literary.
know this but I think it's so helpful to have these reminders of how to invite Christ
into all our daily actions.
And so thank you for allowing me to share this writing that I feel illustrates this
so beautifully and so well for all of us.
Food, faith and fasting with Rita Madden.
Rita Madden is a registered dietician who finds inspiration in the great role that the
a Orthodox Christian faith place in her modern day healthcare.
Please note that the information contained in this podcast is not intended as a substitute for professional medical advice.
Rather, it is provided for educational purposes only.
This has been a listener-supported presentation of Ancient Faith Radio.
Welcome to the Thursday edition of The Path.
You are connected to the path, offering strength for our journey toward salvation.
Here's Father Tom Siroka.
Today's epistle reading is from the first letter of Saint John, chapter 4, verse 20, through
chapter 5, verse 21.
If someone says I love God and hates his brother, he is a liar.
who does not love his brother, whom he has seen, how can he love God, whom he has not seen?
And this commandment we have from him, that he who loves God must love his brother also.
Whoever believes that Jesus is the Christ is born of God, and everyone who loves him who
begot also, loves him who is begotten of him.
this we know that we love the children of God. When we love God and keep His command.
for this is the love of God that we keep his commandments and his commandments.
He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall.
And he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him.
And they will praise and bless and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
Firstienok, chapter 48, verses 4-5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge, but is never the left.
haunted by spirits, angels, demons, and saints. In our time, many year into
break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism to see and to know
reality as it truly is. What is this spiritual reality like? How do we engage
with it well? How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick, and Father Stephen
the young. Host this live Colin show focused on
Enchantment in creation, the union of the scene and unseen as made by God and
experienced by mankind throughout history. Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Good evening. You are listening to the Lord of Spirits podcast. My co-host
Father Stephen DeYoung is with me from Lafayette Louisiana and I'm Father Andrew
Stephen Damick in Emmaus, Pennsylvania. You're not listening to us live. Normally
This is a part where I say if you're listening to a slide call but you're not listening
to us live because this is a pre-recorded episode. So that means that even if you call that number
that you're going to hear the voice of Steve saying you're not going to be able to get through
because Father Stephen is at a retreat and so we're not able to do this one live but we are recording
this. I prefer to call it a strategic withdrawal. Okay, yes, that's true. More of an advance.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, he's gathering his troops together.
So, anyway.
We're still we still wanted to make an episode for you. So here it is. And again, don't
call because no one's going to answer the phone.
I mean, hey, if you want to, I mean, if that's if that's how you get your kick on a Thursday
night, it's calling a number, right? That you know that you know what answers.
That sounds very sad and lonely, but but okay.
They're they're tumors out there who are lined up for that.
So.
Alright, well people often say.
the church isn't a building or you know we could worship anywhere but is that
actually true? Why do ancient Israel end the church worship in buildings? Is it
merely practical to have a roof of our heads or is there a purpose given by God?
Well in this episode we're going to start with the Taj Mahal and end with
parading around corpses. So if you can connect the dots between those you can
and skip this one with the next episode.
If not, though, welcome.
So, Father Stephen, what does the Taj Mahal have to do with the worship spaces of the people
of God?
Well, nothing if you're talking about the casino resort.
I am never talking about the casino resort.
Okay.
Yeah.
So, as is our want when talking about just about anything, we're going to begin at the beginning
of everything.
It's a very good place to start.
Yes, steal my Rogers and Hammerstein joke.
So, and that is paradise, right?
Not by the dashboard light.
Start not the beginning of the late great meatloaf.
But yeah, so some of this here at the beginning are things we've already talked about in
episodes, but we're taking kind of a different trajectory through them this time, as is our
want. And so as we've talked about before, paradise, the word paradise is actually a Persian
loan word that gets taken over into Greek that refers to a particular type of walled garden.
And it is sort of an apt word.
apt design to take over for that because some of the features, including before waterways,
are reflect the description of Eden, of the Garden of God in Genesis, Chapter 2.
So the Taj Mahal is probably the most well-known current example of such a walled...
garden structure that still exists in the world that you can see aerial photos of.
Yeah, if you go to Google Maps and just type in Taj Mahal, again, not going to the casino, but look at the Taj Mahal in India.
and then turn on the satellite photo,
then you can zoom in and you will see
at the Western end, you will see the building
that everyone refers to as a Taj Mahal, which is
And then directly to the east of it,
you will see this walled garden with four quarters in it
and these, there's a fountain in the middle, right?
And are they actually waterways now?
Or I can't really tell from the photo,
but in any event, I think they traditionally are,
that there's water flowing in four directions
out of that fountain that's in the middle.
And so it's, you know, this is an ancient as you see.
said pattern. And I actually wanted to, you know, since I want to look like a
scholar too, just a little bit, I want a chance. It's time. It's time for
Father Andrew's etymology corner inserts public domain string music here.
Yeah. I actually had someone send me a couple of suggested theme themes for
father and his etymology corner that he created himself. So maybe we'll...
when we will see about incorporating them.
Anyway, so yeah, the English word paradise, as you said,
I mean, it's a lone word from Persian into Greek.
And then from Greek, it gets into Latin,
and then from Latin into French,
and then from there actually into very late old English,
where we've got the word, potidies, which becomes,
you know, the origin of our modern English word paradise.
So here's something that's kind of fun though.
before we had paradise in
in Old English.
Earlier Old English had this amazing word, which is
Neorx Noong, which includes the element
wong, which means a field W-A-N-G.
And it seems, you know, linguists are not entirely
sure about this, but it seems that this word
Neorx Noong, which actually you can see in earlier Old English
Transitions of the Bible.
Right, so this is this is a word that does have a Christian history in English.
Although completely gone now, right, there's nothing as far as I know descended from the worst this word in modern English.
But Nierricks, Nguong seems to come from a from Germanic paganism originally and may have referred to a heavenly field or meadow.
So again, you've got this idea of a divine garden, right.
So English has had this concept in it, but then we dragged in paradise.
much later on. I mean nothing wrong with that word is lovely but we did have this awesome word
Nairu Ksnauong, any ORXNAWANG. So there you go, Father Andrews etymology corner.
This has been Father Andrews etymology corner.
Thanks Father. So okay so why I mean we've talked about this a little bit but just kind of review
for those who have not listened to all 84 or whatever it is hours of podcast up to this point.
and counting and counting.
counting. Why is a garden significant as paradise? Like why that image? Why not like,
you know, a big glorious golden mansion or something like that?
Right. And it's not just in Genesis 2 that God lives in a garden, right? This is common in the ancient
that a particular God or the God's, you know,
what we're dealing with is real neighbors live in these sort of garden set.
And clearly ancient Germanic paganism too, you know, the
Neorick Stemont. I just have to say that a lot
of words as many times as I can. Yes.
Was there a bright golden haze on that meadow anyway?
Nice.
So I didn't think you would make so tunes references.
This is really wonderful actually.
Yeah, there is no end to my pop culture sub-referensibility.
pop culture sub-referensibility.
Nice.
There are no boundaries.
So, yeah, so there's on a very surface level.
Not that this is untrue, but this is very surface level.
When you consider the ancient Near East, you consider the terrain.
You consider what most of the land was like outside of the river valleys.
There's a reason why the civilization showed up in Mesopotamia and along the Nile.
Right. Um, there's water. Yeah.
You're dealing with mostly desert and wilderness, right?
And so there's if you're living in sort of a desert wilderness setting,
if you're sort of clinging to a river and hoping for healthy flooding in order to
grow crops and that kind of thing, then sort of a green lush garden is sort of
the dream spot, right? It's sort of the heavenly spot, right?
So on a surface level, you just have that that contrast.
But if you push that contrast a little deeper.
right? In terms of what it really represents, then, you know, as we've talked about before,
what's going on in Genesis 1 and Creation, things being put in order, things being filled
with life, a garden is sort of the perfect combination of that because by virtue of being
a garden, it is ordered, right? It is tended and put in order, but it is also obviously filled
with in producing life.
Right. Right. Right.
And that is over again.
the wilderness which is obviously by virtue of being wilderness is not put in order, is not tended
and comes to represent sort of death because things go out there and die.
Right. And it's fun. Even this word wilderness that we use now, it's often used in a kind of
romantic way like, oh, the pristine wilderness. But I mean in that word is wilderness is the word
wild, right? The concept of wilderness, the wild place.
You know, when the word is conceived in English anyway, it's this sense of a chaotic space where which is dangerous and you know, full of death, right?
Because the pristine wilderness that you would go in and experience as a kind of tourist is just not a thing for most ancient people.
Yes, there are predatory animals out there.
You know, and the hydration and yeah, um all around.
Yeah, most of the ancient Near East is not a good place to try to forage, right?
Like we're not talking about the forests of Europe or something where you can find nuts and berries.
So, so yeah, so, so that is really sort of the deeper and key element.
And as we've talked about before, paradise is wherever God is.
Right.
Right, wherever God is, that place becomes paradise.
And so we see the...
reflected all through our hemnography, right? We call the Theotokos at one point
paradise and doubted with speech. Or a mystical paradise in the canon
across. Right. Because God comes to dwell within her, within her womb. And this
also is then used in the New Testament. Sometimes it's some of the weirder
passages like you and I believe it's John 10 where
uh, Christ promises that people will have rivers of water flowing out of their belly.
Uh, right. Which yeah, we let that run by and we're like, but if you think about that,
that's like, okay, that's kind of a weird image. Yeah, that's the last time I had rivers running out
of my belly, it was because I went to Taco Bell very late night and it was a mistake.
But this is the opposite of that. Yeah. Yeah.
This is the paradise.
Yes, this is talking about the holy...
spirit who is God coming to dwell within a person. And so they become paradise.
And paradise, of course, had four rivers running out of it to water the world.
And that's the idea, right, is that not only will the person who has the Holy
Spirit dwelling within them be filled with life themselves, but that life will
sort of overflow out of them into the world around them. Right. Yeah. And also
that sense.
that paradise is also God's presence with mankind.
So not just wherever God is,
but the sense of a place of communion with God
and being with God.
Yeah, like you said, that wherever God is,
becomes paradise, but of course,
it's the experience of human beings of that.
That is the paradise.
Yeah, exactly, right.
Right.
Right, and this is also why paradise.
could be used in terms of where the righteous go at the time of their death.
Right. Right. It's not saying they go to like Eden as a plot of land somewhere. Right.
Yeah. Or they go to some physical garden space somewhere. Yeah.
They come into the presence of God. Right. And so when Christ says the thief on the cross,
today you will be with me and paradise. That's almost redundant actually. For him to be with Christ,
is
I mean, in a sense, at that moment, even both of them hanging on the cross, he was in paradise.
Right.
Yeah.
So, as we've mentioned before, not only are we talking about a garden, right, as the
place where God dwells, but that garden tends to be situated atop a mountain.
Right.
the mountain of God.
And so we're really starting here.
We made it me didn't lay this out at the beginning, right?
But if we're going to talk about the place where God is among his people,
we have to start with the place where God is and to move from there.
That's why we're starting where we're starting.
But so that is the time of mountain and that mountain is the mountain of God.
Right.
And this again much like
the gardens, right? You see this throughout the ancient Near East, throughout Israel's
neighbors. They have an idea that a God or their gods live on a mountain someplace, right?
Whether it's Mount Zafon, Mount Olympus, right? Take your pick. There's some kind of mountain
or hill or high place where...
where God lives.
So some people who maybe haven't heard us talk about this
before maybe saying,
I don't see anything about a mountain in Genesis too.
Yeah, right.
Right.
It's not explicitly said
and on top of a mountain was Eden.
But what you do get is that there are four rivers
flowing out in four directions,
which the only way that that's possible
is if you're in an elevated space.
Right.
slow downhill.
And should people do that?
Right. They had figured that out.
Yeah. And I think one of the difficulties is
we often read the Bible as discrete pieces rather than as
I think you said in another interview as intertextual
elements that are related to all the other parts of the Bible
all at once. Right. So like for instance,
classic examples.
in Exodus where Moses receives the law, it does not say in that passage that there are angels present and
involved with receiving the law.
But it says that in the New Testament.
And so you have to imagine that and I love this one of the things I love to point out you have to imagine that when the Charlton
Heston Ten Commandments film was made they were not actually looking at those New Testament passages that
made reference to the law being received via angels. They were just looking at the Exodus passage and so then that's what you actually get on the
Screen is Moses.
kind of buy himself with God and he gets the law from God that way but there's no actual angels present
on the screen, right? So this is another one of those examples where in Genesis it does not say
explicitly that it's amounted and of course it's implied as you as you said by the rivers, right?
But you do get other passages that do say that Eden is unamounted, right? It's just not there in Genesis.
Right, that explicit.
Yeah, not explicit.
It not explicit.
Yeah.
So one of those is in Ezekiel chapter 28 verses 23,
verses, excuse me, verses 13 and 14.
And this is actually referencing the devil.
And so it's talking to the devil and says this,
you were in Eden, the Garden of God, every precious stone
was your covering Sardius, Toupaz, and Diamond Barrel.
and Jasper, Sapphire, Emerald, and Carbuncle, and Crafton and Gold were your settings and your engravings.
On the day that you were created, they were prepared.
You were an anointed guardian, Cherub. I placed you.
You were on the holy mountain of God in the midst of the stones of fire.
You walked. And then of course it goes on to say about how God cast him out because he was evil.
But, but there you get it. Eden is on this mountain of God.
of God, it's a garden of God, it's all right there in those couple of verses and Ezekiel.
Yeah, the next verse is basically you are holy and perfect until you weren't right exactly
but
But yeah, so that right there is you're in Eden you are on the holy mountain of God right so this is
That is clear as you can get right so and just just like with the garden
There's sort of a a surface level reason and then we can push a little bit deeper so
surface level reason
That that you usually get is that well
I'll, uh, they
thought the gods were up on the mountains because you know they kind of thought the gods were the sky and mountains are up close to the sky and they're kind of inaccessible right right.
Right.
And you know there's something there right.
High place proximity to the heavens right there there's something there but I mean these mountains were talking about early relatively inaccessible right like Mount Olympus is not Mount Everest.
Right you're not going to die.
You can climb up there yeah yeah and see what's going on right.
So we
we have to push a little deeper to sort of fully get it that.
And one of the interesting ways to push deeper is to see
what all of these cultures and all these people groups see
as the opposite of the mountain of God or the gods.
And that is usually some form of the abyss or tardorus in Greek
or that we've talked about before.
And you find this language you...
for the abyss where it's described as an inverted mountain.
Huh.
As an upside-down mountain.
Yeah, that's weird.
I mean, is the idea that it's like a big hollow mountain?
Because I mean, when I think of the abyss,
I think of like a crack in the earth
that you just fall and fall and fall.
But the, I don't know, how do they conceive of that?
Or...
They're thinking of it as sort of a conical hole.
Yeah.
Right, that you go down in the same way
that you have a peak of a mountain,
you have sort of the depths
of the abyss.
Yes.
Okay.
Right.
And so it is really about this concept of the depths of the underworld, right?
The depths of deep within the earth, below the pillars of the earth, you know, contrasted
with the heights, right?
Yeah.
The ear to the heavens.
And that mountain language actually shows up in an interesting place in the book of Revelation.
Oh yeah.
Right.
Another
one of these passages that it's like so full of this crazy kind of imagery. You can just walk by it and not really realize what's going on. So Revelation 8.8.
The second angel blew his trumpet and something like a great mountain burning with fire was thrown into the sea and a third of the sea became blood.
Which is very disturbed and kind of weird imagery again.
But the abyss in the book of Enoch is not only makes use of that inverted.
mountain language, but has it on fire? Right, a flaming mountain thrown into the sea.
Right, and so what Revelation is talking about there is, you know, the abyss is used
for the depths of the sea, right, it's sort of a sacred geography sets. Right, right.
This is talking about the sea actually becoming the abyss. Oh wow. Right, in Revelation. Right,
Be careful.
the sea if you're someone who lives around the Mediterranean basin, right, is yes,
there's storms blow off of it, it's scary, there's the chaos stuff but also you get fish out of it,
you use it for trade, you use it for life, right. So if the sea goes full of bists on you, right,
you're in a lot of trouble. Yeah, and I know the image of a third of the sea becoming blood,
but you know sort of...
death image for sure.
Yeah.
And remember, I mean, that's obviously borrowing from Exodus.
And Exodus, when the Nile turns to blood, all the life in it dies.
Yeah, right.
It's about, it starts to stink.
Yeah, exactly.
The life characteristic of the water becomes negated by virtue of association with death
in the underworld.
Right.
And so it just becomes fully that, right?
completely chaos, fully destruction.
fully deaf. Yeah, fun with Revelation. Yeah, right. I thought we were not supposed to read that book now.
So the, so then the flip side of the abyss, right, getting back to the mountain of God, right? We see
as we talked about in our sacred geography episode, there are a whole series of holy mountains
through going through the Old Testament.
And those holy mountains all at various points are being the mountain of the mountain of God.
Yeah, we mentioned this. I mean, if you go back and listen to our sacred geography episodes, there's one called the mountain of God, the boat of Thesias that kind of lays out these ideas.
But I think one example I think suffices
to understand this and that is for instance when
if you read closely, if you read Exodus
You
when Moses sees the burning bush and speaks to God in the burning bush, it says in Exodus that
this is Mount Horop. But if you were to ask most people, hey, where did Moses talk to God in the
burning bush? Almost everyone, every Christian, and probably, certainly every Orthodox Christian would
say, oh, that was on Sinai. But if you read Exodus, it says it's Horop. And it gets even further
to confuse if you go to Mount Sinai now and to go to the monastery of St.
which actually is traditionally the monastery of the transfiguration.
They could point you, here is the burning bush.
Here it is here inside the monastery grounds on Sinai.
And so then the question is, well, where did that actually happen?
And I know that sometimes people when trying to work out the geography of the scriptures,
you know they'll try to solve this in a material way by saying well Moses was on
this one mountain, but here it's called Horib and another place it's called Sinai.
But if you understand, take a geography, then what you actually see happening is that Horib
is being the mountain of God when Moses is speaking to him in the burning, you know, with
the burning bush.
And then Sinai is being the mountain of God.
And even is being the place of the burning bush later on by virtue of, again, Moses speaking
there with God by virtue of frankly the monastery.
treating that bush as being the burning bush.
Right? So it is.
Right. So it is.
Yeah, it is the burning bush.
Whether you could establish some kind of genetic connection or prove.
Like, how could you prove? I mean, how many thousands of years ago was that?
You know, it's not like Moses took a DNA sample of the burning bush so that we could analyze it later.
You have to think differently about these things, people.
just say, oh, oh, you know, we can prove through, you know, technology.
that this is this, that's not the point at all.
So the mountain of God is one, but human beings
can experience the mountain of God
on different material mountains, even to the point
that the burning bush itself is on at least
two different material mountains.
Yes.
Yep.
Yeah.
And so, yeah, and we don't need to go back
to everything in that episode.
Right.
I mean, this is just...
Yeah, we have this and it's not even like a fully contemporary materialist view.
Yeah.
Because if again, if you understand that a living human body changes out all its matter
over the course of several years, realize that there are particles of matter that were
part of Christ's human body that are now part of other people's bodies.
Right.
But we don't say that those people's bodies are Christ.
Right, because those individual particles are not being Christ's body now.
Right. Right.
Yeah, and it's funny, when people try to read the Bible and figure out this stuff,
there's two takes on it that are both modernist materialist versions.
There's the take you might describe as a liberal take, which essentially say,
She say, ah, see, look at these contradictions.
There's no way that this is true, or this is made-
up or you know whatever. There's no historical reality whatsoever. Yeah there's no historical reality
whatsoever. And then you've got the other end which is you know and I'm using this word in the
early 20th century since the fundamentalist take on this which is to say no no we can make this
all work out and kind of empirically scientifically prove that this is this you know but both takes are
essentially assuming modernist materialist, a materialist framework.
categories. Yeah, categories exactly. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Which mountain is it exactly? Like, well,
it can be we're saying it can be several. Yeah. Yeah. One at a time, usually, but but but but only
usually. Right. Right. Because I mean, that you know, not to get too far ahead of ourselves, but
you know, Mount Athos can be the mountain of God at the same time that I'm experiencing the
the mountain of God here in Emmaus, Pennsylvania.
Yeah.
You know, and let's say caverns is at the mountain of God.
Yeah, right. Yep.
So, um,
right, so we've now, we're now at
Garden on a mountain. Okay. Right. And so,
this we've talked about a few times, I think.
So people are probably used to that, but
we've got one more step to go here, right?
And that's that, um,
God or the gods, depending on, you know,
again who we're talking about here.
Was it just viewed to sort of hang out and lounge and look jury in in said garden on top of the mountain?
I like to flash the Titans where they just sort of hanging out around some eating ambrosia here.
Yeah, leading on a couch.
Yeah.
So because of course they conducted business and this sort of thing right and and the way they did that was really intense.
Right, so
The idea was that they had actual tents.
And this is not just tents that we think of tents,
like they were all camping up there.
Yeah, this is not the winter of our discount tents.
Wow.
That was uncalled for.
So we have to bleep that out.
Ha ha ha!
This is not like, you know, you may be picturing from some Roman military movie, you know,
the military camp with all the tents, right?
Yeah, right.
Not that sort of thing.
So we're talking about the kind of tents that nomadic peoples of the ancient Near East lived in.
So, these were big tents, right?
And the way this
typically function was that sort of the head of the remember we're not talking about
nuclear families we're talking about big extended families big households that included
you know there was there was some patriarch figure at the head of it right and then then
you also had all the sons and daughters their kids all the cousins all the aunts and uncles
are all together, plus all the higher-
servants plus all the indentured servants plus all the slaves plus you know
the animals the families of all of those servants and slaves right in this huge
organization right this huge clan structure okay and so the people who were
members of the family who were at the head of the clan typically were in one
large sort of pavilion tent. And the way that worked was...
when someone came of age and got married.
So when one of the sons or grandsons
of the patriarch or the Potter familiarists,
came of age and got married,
which would typically be around 13.
So it was when they became basically physically mature
to be married off, right?
And marriages were all arranged, right?
Probably to a cousin, right?
from yep.
And then, but then, so they are now going to form,
they're going to begin having their own children.
A portion of that large tent would be sort of sectioned off.
They would hang up like partitioned curtains.
Yeah. Right.
So there would be this new area of the tent
that that couple would have.
Hmm. Right.
And these things would kind of get reshuffled
when there was a new head of the whole family, right?
But
other than that, it was fairly constant. So this is this kind of arrangement is
how typically and we're going to go now to the Bale cycle, right, as one
example of this, how the northern Canaanites and later Phoenicians saw this. This
is how they saw their gods living. Because remember as we talked about a little
but last time there's other,
their gods has been related genealogically.
So this is kind of big tent paganism then.
Yes.
Sorry, I have to get my jokes in here when I've got them.
So, for example, using the Bale Cycle and those gods as example,
L, who's sort of the most high god and the father of the gods,
those two being sort of equivalent titles.
has this big tent in which the gods and goddesses who are considered to be his children have their own spaces.
And so in the Bale Cycle those spaces for the other gods are referred to as the Seven Rooms, which are those sort of sectioned off places.
place it so they had their own place, right? And so then a big part of the over our
arch of the bail cycle is that bail sort of doesn't have his own place within
L's tent and his sister slash wife a not who is a very violent
Wargottis gives out this rant, right, to L, her dad.
about how
Bale should have his own place and if L does it give it to him
She's going to crush his skull until his beard is soaked with a bore and
You can read the Bale cycle online English translation everybody if you want to see what's actually looks like it's it's it's a it's a beautiful
beautiful religion. Yes. I was told that paganism is peaceful and nice and
and Steve Gallagher.
Korean and stuff, but yeah, well, it is a woman threatening to go out out not a man. So there you go women's voices being heard
So yeah, it's but you can see here too as we've talked about before right like
We saw how a Daniel seven some of the L imagery is used for for God the Father, right, right?
So you see the relationship between the gods of the nations and the most high
sort of reflected here. Yeah, obviously this is super functional family. Right, and it's not friendly.
Right. Yeah. They're making demands, they're issuing threats. Right. And so then, you know, the
big part of the arc as we described it before in the bail cycle is it sort of ends up with bail
building his own palace. Right. In the other world, after he totally wins, like totally.
it.
Feet's everywhere.
I'm surprised this is not a teacher.
It's a go battle.
What you're saying right now.
So yeah, so that's sort of that.
Now, obviously, there's a lot of discontinuity between that.
Right.
And the view that the Israelites are going to hold.
But they do have this.
This view that there is sort of this.
They they went when this is talked about.
talked about they don't primarily see.
the God of Israel as living in a big castle or palace,
they have this tent idea.
And one of the very, there's a very familiar place
in the New Testament where this comes out
but it kind of gets buried by the English translations.
Right, right.
There's that point where Jesus is talking to his disciples
about, you know, when he's about to ascend into heaven
and you said you...
he's going to prepare a place for them and he has this line and here's the version that most people probably know in my father's house are many mansions
which of course then is the inspiration for that classic old I don't know if it's a Baptist song but a lot of Baptists sing it you know I've got a
mentioned just over the hilltop, right? We got this image of a kind of strange sort of suburban heaven.
But yeah, with the dimensions. Exactly.
Yeah, exactly.
Right, but, but no, it's not in my father's house or many
mansions. It's really in my father's tent are many partitions.
Is right? The image that we're that Christ is really saying, which means that we're going to,
you know, that Christians are going to live with him as part of this extended family.
Right? It's not that everybody has their own great little nuclear family
mansion, you know, I mean, think about that for a second, right?
If every Christian has a mansion just over the hilltop, does
anyone live with each other? You know, is there an actual
communion or love going? You know, like it's everybody's got
their own private like this is hell. Hell is where everybody's,
you know, it's somehow, somehow everybody's mansion is inside
one house too. Yeah. In my father's house. So it doesn't even
make sense as a translation. No. Yeah. Yeah. But it's this is,
This is the end of this being...
used and of course it's not just image of being part of God's family and
dwelling with God, right? But there's also also in contained in that when Christ
said that is this notion of theoses because he's referencing an image that
they would have known which is the image of the gods all living together in a
big tent. The sons of God, right? The sons of God would be the ones who have their
own partitions within the big, yeah, right, within the big tent. Yeah, and that's not
end of the episode everybody.
But it's a great little conclusion to some of this
that we've just been talking about.
But we're not even in the first half.
And just as a tease, that understanding,
remember, it's the sons who have the place in the tent, right?
Like the slaves of the servants don't, right?
And so think of all the language in St. Paul
about distinguishing us as sons of God from slaves,
or servant, right?
this plays this
understanding plays into all of that, but we can't go down that rabbit hole right now.
Maybe future episode.
In a future episode.
Mark off your bingo card.
So when you kind of put this all together, right, our big tent in our garden on a mountain,
right, you get to the idea we've talked about before of the mountain of assembly, right,
in Hebrew, Harmoeid.
And we've talked about it before, how that is actually what gets
transliterated into Armageddon in Revelation.
Yeah.
Has nothing to do with Mekido.
I'm sorry.
I know we want to find physical places for everything.
But it has nothing to do with Mekido.
It has to do with the nations motivated by demonic powers
laying siege to the mountain of God.
Right.
Harmoid.
And the reason you get a G in there is that Mowade has language
shirts.
Moeid has an ion in it, which was originally pronounced as a kind of a sound.
Yeah, sort of a glottal, almost a glottal stop almost.
Right, so the E and Harbo-
Harbo-Aid is pronounced or expelled, it transliterated, I should say, in English,
H-A-R, Har, that means mountain.
And then assembly is Moeid, it's usually transliterated, M-O-E-D.
And the E there is the ion.
Yeah, the ion.
And some of you if you imagine replace.
that you with a G so it's M O G D. Yeah.
Harmony. Yeah. You can see how you get Armageddon out of it. Right. Right.
That's probably it's that's Father Steven's
biology corner. There you go.
Nothing like nothing like
Gunnourls. Anyway.
So this is the mountain of assembly
because this is the gathering place of the Devine Council.
Right. This is a
place where they gather in the tents.
And so this is, as we mentioned, right?
This is depending on your neighbor of Israel, right?
There are several mountains of God in Israel, but they, you know,
there's a phone, a phone, if we're talking about bail,
Olympus, if we're talking about the Greeks,
and you could throw in here.
Am I a bit of Norse mythology?
Yeah, not exactly...
exactly a neighbor of Israel, but you've got human Björg, which is, which actually is
interestingly is Heimdall's mountain, but it does actually mean the heavenly mountain
or the heavenly fortress, because fortresses and mountains are pretty much the same thing
in ancient Germanic.
You build them on the high place.
Exactly.
And weirdly enough, it's also a term that's used for where you bury people, because it's
usually in hills and stuff.
So there's that sense of the inverted.
You've got the inverted mount and kind of...
into the word, but yeah, this sort of heavenly mountain where the gods are, with some variation
between mythology is just exactly what that means. But there's always some kind of council meeting
happening. Where they get, right? And this shows us that Saint Peter knew what was going on,
actually, even though we tend to pick on him a lot, on the amount of transfiguration.
Hmm right
So on the amount of transfiguration when he sees Christ
Conversing with Moses and Elijah and he suggests that they build tents
Right
On top of the mountain for them
We're brave Booths
It's translated in some
But yeah, it's this idea
Manches
I hope you're about your construction number there
Yeah, yeah
So yeah, so he he understands.
He's watching a divine council meeting. Yeah, right. That's what he understands is happening here
And that's why he thinks that would be the appropriate thing to do right right
Because this is the image and the understanding he has in his mind. Yeah, and so
All this means now
Right, and this is this is where we're gonna you know
We're actually gonna, I think we're gonna actually get to our topic in the second half tonight rather than waiting till
third half. But so when Moses goes up on the mountain of God, right, to receive the Torah,
right, he goes up there, when they send him up there, because everybody else is terrified,
right? You go, yeah, because they see all the thunder and the lightning and all that kind
of stuff going the darkness, shroudings, the peak. They're like, yeah, yeah, you go, you go see
see what's going out up there, Vosis.
Let us know.
We'll go back to us.
Yeah.
Vosis is, this is where.
Moses is going. Right. Moses is going up to the peak of the mountain. He's going up to the garden. He's going up to where the divine council is meeting.
He's entering into this into this tent. Right. And this is why this understanding is why you have as you as you alluded to earlier, you have these texts in the New Testament that refer to the law being given by the law.
being given by
or through angels. Like St. Stephen refers to it in his sermon in Acts 7.53, gets
referred to in Hebrews 2 verse 2. St. Paul develops it a little more in Galatians 3, 19 and 20,
but that's because there, St. Paul is wanting to point out that it was Christ Himself serving as
a mediator who gave the law through the angels.
When you throw in verse 20.
Because if you just read verse 19, again, if you chop things up and don't read context,
it says it was given, you know, by angels through a mediator, right?
You might think, oh, Moses, right?
But if you read verse 20, St. Paul immediately says, now mediator implies more than one,
but we know that God is one.
Right.
It's God one.
Yeah.
So who's he talking about?
It's Christ.
because it's funny because he's not...
not countering the idea of it being Moses.
He's sort of countering the idea
of there being a second God.
Right. Right. Right. Right. Right.
Right. And so if he was just talking about Moses,
then saying that makes no sense.
No, exactly.
It's irrelevant to anything. Right.
But he's he is picking up on a further elaboration
of this tradition that you can see, for example,
in the book of Jubiles. Right.
So the book of Jubiles,
sort of the frame story is Moses on top of them out.
Right.
So...
So Moses sort of receives the contents of Genesis 1 through 11 as sort of an apocalyptic
vision, for example.
Right?
And so Jubilee's has all these elaborations.
But so not only is in Jubilee's, is Moses there in the Divine Council and there are angels
through whom the Torah has received.
In addition to the angels plural, there is one particular being the angel of the Presence
Who is this angel of the Lord figure that we talked about in the episode so named?
the angel of Yahweh, right, this figure.
And so that's what St. Paul is really referencing there in Galatians 3.
He's referencing not only the angel's plural being there,
but also this figure, right?
And this figure who isn't Yahweh the God of Israel, right?
Who St. Paul is not so subtly when you know the context,
identifying with Christ.
But so the important part of this
is that when Moses goes up there and enters into this tent
and where the divine council is, and bears witness all this
and receives the Torah, when he comes back down
and we start talking about worship spaces for humans,
beginning with the tabernacle.
The tabernacle is made after the pattern of what
he saw on the mountain.
Right. And Hebrews says so. Right. Exactly. Okay. So this is Hebrews chapter 8 verses 1 through 6. And you'll hear this. You'll hear this in here.
Now the point in what we are saying is this. We have such a high priest, one who is seated at the right hand of the throne of the majesty in heaven, a minister in the holy places in the true tent that the Lord set up not man.
For every high priest is appointed to offer
and sacrifices, thus it is necessary for this priest also to have something to offer.
Now if he were on earth, he would not be a priest at all, since there are priests who offer gifts according to the law.
They serve a copy and shadow of the heavenly things.
For when Moses was about to erect the tent, he was instructed by God saying,
see that you make everything according to the pattern that was shown you on the mountain.
But as it is, Christ has obtained a ministry that is as much more excellent than the old.
Excellent. Then the old...
as the covenant he mediates is better since it is enacted on better promises.
Yeah, it's interesting that line from verse 5, see that you make everything according to the pattern
that was shown you on the mountain. I imagine one reading of that might be to say, oh,
God gave him a kind of sort of blueprints for the tavernacle, but if we understand
what he saw on the mountain, it's no no no. Right. You were in the tent of God
and so go make that down there.
Right, and that's the beginning of verse 5 that they're a copy and shadow of the heavenly things.
Exactly.
Right, yeah.
Yeah.
Alright, well that is our first half.
I'm going to take a short break, and we will be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your
calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
Let's see.
558F Radio.
New from Ancient Faith Publishing.
Orthodoxy and heterodoxy.
Finding the way to Christ in a complicated religious landscape, written by Andrew Stephen
Damick.
The purpose of this book is not to prove that Orthodox Christianity is the one true faith.
I do not believe that it is possible to prove that, at least, not by what can be written
in a book.
We are seeking to do, however, proceeding from the position of the Orthodox Christian
faith is to show that the differences between Orthodoxy and other faiths are real, and
that they are important.
Orthodoxy and heterodoxy, finding the way to Christ in a complicated religious landscape.
Now available as an audiobook at audible.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Even to young if you have a question call now at 855
237-2346. That's 855-AF radio.
Welcome back. This is the second half of the show.
Again, though, we're not taking any calls,
despite what you heard from the Voice of Steve,
because this is a pre-recorded episode,
because Father Stephen is a way at a retreat
when we normally would be airing this live.
So we'll be back in a few...
episode live, but it's gonna be a little while. So, all right, well, we just finished up talking about
that passage from Hebrews chapter 8, where it references that Moses is told by God to make the
tabernacle after the pattern of what he saw when he was up on the mountain of God, that tent there,
that he saw there. So, that's where we left off. And, all right, well, as you mentioned, we're
We're actually get to our official state and top.
which is the Tabernacle right here in the second half.
So, yeah.
Yeah, what we're talking about before was intense,
and now this is gonna be even more intense.
Yes.
The, so the dad joke listed this episode is already very,
very, very long.
Yes, yes.
And really, a lot of these were going back to the same well,
just over and over again, but milking it.
Oh.
I'm Dutch. We do dairy farming. It's a thing.
There you are. Yeah.
So, uh, the tabernacle, right, as such is a tent shrine, right?
And it's not the only tent shrine in the ancient Near East.
It is a little unusual in that it is presented as, uh, in the Torah,
and treat it as if, at least in the early.
historical books as permanent. Yeah. Right. As this being this trench shine is going to be the sort of
permanent shrine temple for Yahweh the God of Israel, whereas typically Asian areas, those were
you'd have a temple, the permanent temple would be a permanent physical building.
I mean I was stoned.
And yeah.
Right.
and and tent shrines, then we're usually used
on sort of temporary and occasional basis,
or bacy's.
So one example is we have an uveritic ritual
where at a certain time of year,
they would sacrifice a donkey
and they did it at a particular spot.
And so they put up a 10.
shrine at that spot at that time, and then they would go and get the idols, the bodies of the gods,
and sort of process and haul them out to the tent shrine, offer them the donkey sacrifice, and then
sort of take them all back home.
I don't know.
No, no, no, no.
It's her temples.
With this donkey sacrifice, it's something that the people-
eat as well or is it like a whole burn? Yes. So they would eat them. So and since you you know you
become what you're in communion with then through this sacrifice they were literally making
asses of themselves. Wow. Thank you very much. Wow. I didn't actually even write that joke down
before and it just came to me. Next pre-record we're doing in the evening because
am I too punny in the morning? Is that the problem? A little bit. Yeah. This amount of punishment.
more than it's more coffee.
more than we could take.
Monocoffian me this morning.
So you let your children sort of wear you down a little bit.
Every year.
Come back when you've been beat up by your kids a little bit, Father.
Yeah.
And so, right, so it's that kind of temporary thing and not a permanent.
And this is what sort of creates the tension when we get to David, right?
sort of culturally and everything. David is thinking.
Hey, this is weird, right?
I've got a capital city now.
I have a permanent home, right?
Shouldn't the God of Israel also, right?
Yeah, there's an online in the Psalms where he says,
you know, I'm not gonna sleep
until I've made a place, a habitation for the God of Jacob, right?
Right, right.
And so there's this idea that,
So he's aware that this is a regular because...
this is irregular for the ancient world, right?
But we have to remember that one of the constant themes
all through the Old Testament was that Israel
was never really supposed to fully settle in the land.
Right.
Right, because as it says, a Deuteronomy,
you know, now out here in the wilderness,
you're dependent on me, you know,
and things already weren't going that great in the wilderness.
But, you know, what's your-
get into the land and you settle down and you plant crops and you harvest the year after
year and you plant vineyards and everything you're going to forget about God.
And you're going to sort of fall away from all this.
And so there's constant things like the Feast of Tabernacles.
Yeah, to bring them back out to go live and breathe.
Bring them back out.
Yeah, so okay, so a question just occurred to me, you know, obviously we're not saying,
David has this idea that he needs to build.
temple, something actually more permanent. And I mentioned that line from the Psalms where he says
he's not going to rest until he's made a habitation for the God of Jacob. And I haven't checked whether
any of the fathers interpret this way or if there's any indication in the New Testament that this
gets interpreted. But could we say that David fulfilled his own prophecy by being the ancestor of the
Theotokos? Right, yeah, by being the ancestor of Christ. Yeah, yeah, that he... Through the Theotokos,
became the grandparent of Jack.
Christ. He does form a habitation for the God of Jacob by, you know, through his
his distant granddaughter. Right. Yeah. And in terms of the physical building, God is always sort
of resistant to David on it. Yeah. Like, no, no, that's not. Yeah. Right. And so again, part of
this is, you know, yeah, God's got settled. You shouldn't be either. Right. That you should
continue to, right. And we're going to get more into that later in this half. We're going to
We're going to talk more about...
when the temple actually gets built and why,
and more of the reasons why God was resistant to it.
But so we're going to start with the tabernacle,
because the tabernacle is, you know,
if you've read through the book of Exodus,
you've read in excruciating detail.
Right.
Everything about the tabernacle, its construction,
and the furnishings and all of that twice.
Yeah, it's basically blueprints
and architectural plans in verbal form.
Yes, and so.
So first you have all the instructions and then you have the narrative of them fulfilling
the exact same instruction.
So you literally read it twice in the same level of detail.
And so we're going to kind of start on the outside and work our way in.
Okay.
Right.
To give an idea of what the tabernacle as pattern looked like.
So
We're starting with the outer court.
Right.
When we think of the tabernacle, we tend to just think of the tent.
But the tent of the tabernacle is inside a sort of courtyard
that's formed by hanging curtains.
Right.
So there's a demarcation.
Yeah.
And if you go and just like do a Google image search, really,
just type in tabernacle and do a Google image search on it,
you will come up with a lot of diagrams and images
that are pretty good.
for this. Yeah, yeah, the first one was kids made in Sunday school.
And I have to say, so my great, great grandfather, who is a Baptist preacher up in New England,
he had a thing that he did. So I mean, he served at a bunch of churches up there, but he also had
like a touring talk that he did about the tabernacle, and he had some kind of model that he would
take around with him and give sort of tours of it to people, you know, and explain it and so
You
So yeah, and I've seen actually I saw flyer for this at one point. It's it's maintained in my somewhere in my family's archives.
So, so yeah, I mean, this is totally a thing and especially if you grew up, you know, kind of low church Protestant, you've probably seen these models, like you said, stuff that your kids built and in Sunday school and all that kind of stuff.
But yeah, there's a lot of pretty decent diagrams and, you know, illustrations and stuff that you can find online.
And you'll see, like you said, I think there's this...
in the middle and then there's a kind of fence all the way around it made with curtains effectively,
although it's not like curtains like you're having your living room. No, this is structural curtains,
you know, essentially. Yeah, like you'd use for the side of a tent. Yeah. Right. Exactly. Yeah.
There's a tent fence and then there's a, you know, and then a tent in the center and there's a big
courtyard that's made by the fence. Right. Right. And frankly, a lot of the stuff that we think about
as happening in the town.
Abernakul actually happened in the outer court.
Yeah, right.
Right.
So it's in this outer court area.
So this is where you have, this is where sacrifice
is take place.
This includes the area called the Prothesis, which
is where the animal was sort of butchered and separated
or for talking about wheat cakes, where the cakes were
separated and sorted and whatever was being sacrificed,
where it was sort of portioned out and everything.
However, it needed to be.
I'm sorry.
before the actual sacrifice.
But then the two major pieces of furniture in this area
to sort of facilitate that, right?
Were the copper laver,
right?
Which is a big bowl on a stand.
Right.
Yeah, a big copper bowl on a stand.
But the word laver shows up in a lot of.
That word laver.
Adiocune translations.
It does.
I think it's from the King James, is where you're using it.
Yeah, it is.
Yeah, yeah.
And so you get a lot of, if you read, if you read a, uh, uh,
Quastance, uh, patrology, uh, he loves that word.
Um, so, uh, but so yeah, big cover ball to state.
It's full of water, right?
And that water is used for, uh, was used for ritual washings for the
priests.
Right.
As they're coming in and going out, coming into the courtyard, going
from the courtyard into the tent proper, right?
And that's to sort of wash off whatever uncleanness.
They've brought with them primarily hands and feet right right watching their hands and watching their feet
um and
So that is there and then the other major piece of furniture is that the one we probably think about most of the courtyard is the altar of burnt offering
Okay, right, so both the place where the sacrifices are prepared and
And the place where the sacrifices are offered is in this outer court.
Okay, so there's kind of two tables up.
there. The one where they're actually burnt stuff is burnt up.
Right. That's not really a table. That's more of like a big grill.
Oh, it just holds. Yeah. But that's the altar of burnt offering.
Right. Okay. And suddenly there's probably more of a table, which is for
into the pro thesis for for butchery, separating and cutting. You know, right, right?
Right. Right. And so, um, as as we've mentioned before, right, people would come to
the entrance.
right and give whatever they were sacrificing right it would be taken into the court guard by the priest they would
They would take it to the pro thesis. They get everything arranged how they wanted to they go and offer the portions that are being offered to God on the altar of
Bern offering and then come back and give the
Offer whatever parts are for them and keep the parts that are for the priest now they would stay outside the offers
Yes, yeah, they don't get to go into the fence right right
Right. They did get you to just go there and mill around.
Yeah, I mean, there's a lot of references.
I've noticed this in Exodus and Leviticus and Numbers.
There's a lot of references to people being brought to the gate of the tabernacle.
Right.
And lots of things happening right there at that gate.
So these two things, right, you can see, and this is especially, I mean, it's kind of obvious
that the
the labor, this washing, that this is sort of preparatory purification,
right, like for service, right, in the tabernacle. But the same applies to the sacrifices.
Right. The most of the sacrifices, right, most of the sacrificial system is aimed at establishing
and continuing communion with God to allow
for what's going to go on inside the actual tabernacle.
Hmm. So what's happening out in the outer courts is prep for going into the the the holy place,
right? Right. So it's purification. It's allowing God to continue to dwell there, allowing people to draw
near without experiencing death by holiness, right?
Yeah.
Yeah, and so then as we move into the holy place, right, this is the more substantive part, right, of what's going on.
Right. And this is hidden by this inner tent.
Right. And this is, there are going to be certain priests who are allotted at certain times to have this inner ministry, right.
And the reason I say this is more central is that
When we get glimpses, right, we already talked about how Moses is constructing this as an icon as a representation of what he saw on the mountain.
But when we see, for example, Isaiah or Zeeheel, right, C heavenly worship or St. John for that matter, C heavenly worship, right, the heavenly worship they see is not the stuff that's going on in the courtyard.
Hmm.
They don't see people offering animal sacrifices and washing their hands.
Right. Right.
What they see in the heavenly sanctuary is what goes on inside the tent.
Right. And again, we should, we should just, just to double down,
the tent here is deliberately patterned after this tent that is the dwelling
place of God with, you know, the sons of God that mount, that Moses sees on the mountain.
Right. Yeah. Right.
And so now as we move into the tent, right?
proper right now there's going to be the back portion of the tent the most holy place is sectioned off
right by this heavy curtain right and as we've talked about before only the high priest could go
back there only one day a year on the day of atonement so in the tent then there's a kind of larger
space and then then there's the the innermost place that's sectioned off within that tent right where
Most of the time, nobody go, right?
Right.
So most of the the worship is taking place obviously outside of that curtain but within the tent proper right of the tabernacle.
And so we've got some more pieces of furniture right in here.
We've got that we talked about recently the table of the showbred.
The King James spelled.
And we talk about the bread of the Presence, right, that this is the table where the bread is not to feed to God, but through which God feeds the priests who are in there during their allotted service, right, to strengthen them for service, right, so they can carry out their duties.
And it's important that they're fed in there because again, there's this whole elaborate thing about them coming and going, right?
This will be...
allows them to remain there and be strengthened.
And then central to the tabernacle
is the altar of incense, which is a horned altar.
Right.
Which kind of looks like, it's hard to describe exactly
what it looks like.
But it's sort of a plinth of sorts.
Like there are stone versions of this.
I'm assuming the version that they carried around with them
would not have been stone.
Or would not.
Right.
You could read all the details of the.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, exactly. Yeah. So it's sort of a plant.
Um, flat place on top and then there's four bits that stick up on the corners.
And these are regarded as the horns of the altar. They're not actually made of animal horns. It's just their horn shaped.
Right. And so the overall effect is, it's almost like a brazier, but a brazier is usually kind of more basket shaped on top.
But it's the same sort of idea, you know, that you got this flat spot where the incense gets burned.
and then these
these four horns sticking up on the corners.
Right, coals are kindled on that and kept burning on that.
It's sometimes slightly cupcake, not like a bowl,
but a little concave.
And you have the coals burning in there
and then incense is offered on the coals.
And then when you're using a sensor from that,
that was used to transport incense.
So one of the coals and some incense was taken
from the altar of his
it says put it into the sensor and that would then make it mobile, right?
So, yeah, it starts taking the,
taking this sacrifice being offered on this altar kind of on the road, so to speak,
or out, you know, out, out, out from the altar itself.
It, in order to bring the purifying effects of the offering to some particular place or thing.
Right.
Yeah.
And again, the style of the inset's altar.
is not as you alluded to, you've probably picked plenty of pictures of stone ones.
It wasn't like a completely different style than other ones of the ancient Near East, right?
Slightly different composition of materials, but there may have been very similar ones for materials
that we just don't have anymore because, you know, we're in the case.
And again, if you go to Google Image Search and just type in InSenseAlter,
in between stuff from video games interestingly enough, you can see,
You
can see various drawings that seem to basically fit, that would be this sort of thing.
Yeah. It's like when you search for Lord of Spirits, you either get this podcast or a bunch
of anime stuff. Right. There is a whole new thing I've just never done. So not related
it anyway. I am not a wee bladey as a gentleman. Anyway. So, and then the other major piece
of
in that space is the candle stand,
which we now probably think of as a menorah, right?
The seven branch lampstand.
And sometimes...
Sometimes there are seven.
Yes, so people ask, why are there seven lights?
Don't ask Picard.
He gets all worked up about this.
How many lights there are.
But...
Or...
There are four lights.
Yeah, there are seven lights
seven lights because there are
seven planets. So what are the seven planets? Those being the the Sun, the Moon, Mercury,
Venus, Mars, Jupiter and Saturn. Right. I've got planets, you know, defined differently than we do
in the modern era, you know, because this is what they call a geocentric model of the universe.
They're planets because they're wanderers and they don't follow the general track of the stars.
Right, because that's a word swallow predictable pattern.
Plan it means wanderer.
Yes, so right. And so the fact that we don't hold to that cosmology anymore is not relevant to this. No, because the point is right you have these seven lights within within the tent, right as there are seven lights in the sky under the heavens, right.
Right, right. There's this concept then that the tabernacle itself is a microcosm of
the universe and this is being represented by this seven branch candlestand.
Right. Because ultimately where does God live? He doesn't live in a place outside his creation.
Right. Right. He lives in his creation. Right. Right.
And of course within this, don't not contain by it.
Yes. It should make that just like he wasn't detained by the tabernacle.
Exactly right. Yes.
And then of course, as we mentioned before, woven into the veils, the sides of the tabernacle
and into the curtain before the hoiopolis are images of Cherubim, the heavenly throne
guardians.
So there is this iconographic recreation of the Divine Council as well.
And the primary were
the first commandment on worship that's given in the Torah is that incense is to be offered
at morning and evening with prayer. And so that's the kindling of the lamps and the trimming
of the lamps at morning and evening, meaning sunrise and sunset, really. And so this incense
This is the sort of regular pattern, right?
And it's what...
we see, as we mentioned a little bit ago, when we see the worship of heaven, you know,
when you go to Isaiah and he's standing there in the divine council and this, this worship
is being offered, there's an incense altar there, right? And you see angelic beings with
sensors, right? Revelation, right, across the board. This is the worship. So this is what's
going on inside the tent by those designated priests at designated times, unless you want
and it ended up like they had to have an app.
who, right, with even a particular recipe for the incense, right, that all allows them
to draw this close, right? Then you get to the most holy place or the holy of holies, right,
the sanctum sanctorum minus Dr. Strange. And he's taught the strains meant to be a priest.
who need the next time, but no, he's not.
He's not.
No, but he does call his, he calls his house in Greenwich Village, his sanctum, sanctum.
I know. That's the reference. Okay.
I know. No, I know. I know. Okay.
So within the most holy place, obviously the most prominent thing while it was still around
before Ethiopians or whoever else took it, is the Ark of the Covenant, right?
Right.
And.
We talked last time about how the differences between the Ark of the Covenant and idols, right, and how that works.
But again, you have this imagery of the cherubim at the footstool of the throne of God, right, and that footstool language is important, right, because it's not that God, they thought God lived inside the box.
Right. But that this.
This is the point of contact.
If you're going to meet with the king and make a request,
you bow down by his feet.
Where he's enthroned and you make your request.
This is a point of contact.
And then of course the other stuff that was back there,
at least for a while,
in the arc were
the two tablets of the covenant, right? Right? Right?
And just to reiterate, this is two copies.
It's not, Commandments 1 through 5 and then 6 through 10.
No, it's not that they read out of space, right?
Commandments are really short in Hebrew.
They read out of space, it wasn't making some kind of point about,
well, these are about God and these are about your neighbor.
None of that is original. It's two copies of the same covenant, right?
And that's because...
As I believe we mentioned before, it was common when a covenant was issued in the ancient
Ereas that there would be two copies. One, the king would keep because he was going to, right?
Obviously, he was party to it. He was the one issuing the covenant. He was going to then enforce it.
The other one was taken and placed at the feet of the God in the idol of the God, obviously,
in the temple, right? The body of the God of the temple, they place it at his feet.
so that the God was called upon to bear witness to the covenant,
and help with the enforcement.
Right. So in Israel, their king and their God is Yahweh.
Right. So both copies are put in the ark at his with stool.
Right. He's the one issuing the covenant and the one enforcing it and God.
And then, not in the arc.
I know.
Think these were.
in the ark but they were not in the ark. They were next to the ark.
Next the ark.
In the Holy Holies.
Were the jar of mana.
Okay.
And Aaron's rod that budded, that designated him as the eye priest.
Right.
Right. Those two things were kept there also and they disappear even before the
ark does.
Hmm.
And there's a comment in the Old Testament that they had
disappeared at a certain point. But we're
ever told how wise. Yeah, as I say, no sense that God took them or that someone stole them or
they're just gone. No. And I mean, the arc disappears and we're not even actually told that they
realized it had disappeared at a particular point. But we are actually told at one point that
they're like, well, the arcs there, the tablets are still at it, but there's other stuff's gone. Yeah.
Yeah.
So, right there.
So that's the tabernacle with those are the contents. Yeah, the outer courts, the the inner tent with its two partitions.
The accoutremal exactly with all of its furniture and so forth.
And as you said, though, David thought that there needed to be a stone temple because he's got his Jerusalem now and David lives in a nice house shouldn't God live in nice house.
Right. There's a certain logic to it. Yeah. Right. There's a certain logic to it.
Um, but
But beyond even just what we talked about, right, about God wanting to try to help Israel
not feel so settled, there are other issues.
Yeah, okay.
Okay, so we have a what, right?
What else is going on there?
And, you know, and surprise, surprise paganism is involved.
Yeah.
So, so I mean, it's very clear, right?
I mean, you...
He's pretty clear with David.
I don't really want this.
And then when David really pushes through, he says,
you know, well, you're not doing it.
Right.
And basically for Bids, David to do it.
Solomon ends up doing it.
And doesn't see any instructions on how to build it.
Right.
And he says, he says your son will build it.
But even that is, isn't I want your son to build it?
It's your son's going to do it.
Right.
Like, right.
And then even with Solomon, there's this admittal.
You
God doesn't give, you see the excruciating detail given twice in Exodus for the Tabernacle.
Right. And there is nowhere the Old Testament, any kind of similar instructions for the temple.
We get a description of the temple and what Solomon did. But he's never sort of commanded.
Now there is this verse, there's somebody out there already listening to this.
Right.
That they probably forgot we're not
live and they picked up the phone to try and call an um actually us with this verse and first chronicles 28
that talks about David giving Solomon plans right and David says hey I planned everything out
the way God put it in my heart right but okay and they're going to say no God did give David
play and see? Yeah, I mean, but the thing is is that it's such a contrast to the way that God
out the tavernacle. Like so he's gonna tell Moses with all these sort of blueprint kind of language,
and then he's just gonna sort of put it in David's heart. You know, and here's the thing,
it's just David saying that. There's no point where it says, and the word of the Lord came to David,
King of Israel and said unto him. Yeah, and what David is literally saying in the original is,
God put it on my heart to build him a temple, and here's the plans I came up with.
Yeah.
right which is not the same thing right right so I'm looking at the verse it says hear me my brothers
and my people I had it in my heart to build a house of rest for the ark of the covenant of the
Lord and for the footstool of our God and I made preparations for building and then verse three
but God said to me you may not build a house for my name for you are a man of war and I've said blood
so immediately it's followed by like no no yeah but so here's the play in Solomon right here's
That's what I was for.
God right yeah yeah so yeah right and and you really see this brought out when you read
when you read the long prayers about about there's this long prayer Solomon gives it the
dedication of the temple and then there's sort of God's response right and and there's a noted
there's a very noted contrast there because Solomon is very much like you know
Lord,
Yahweh, God of Israel, asks, answer all the prayers of those who pray toward this building.
Yeah. And everything they ask for, give it to them, and do whatever we want
when we do the ritual in the building. Right? It's very much in that direction.
I am a pagan. I'm going to enchant the building, right? So it'll be a magic building.
and God's response is
is basically like I don't live in buildings made by human hands. I don't want this. I don't need this.
This is not how this works. This is not how it works. And then sort of ends up with but
I will condescend to dwell here and you know I will answer your prayers when they're the right
prayers and I will. Right. And so God very much.
not just continues to express
that turbulence but says this is a
condescension and he's not going
to be limited by it.
Right.
He says I'm going to place my name
here.
I'm going to put my presence here
and have that dedication.
It is filled with the Theophane
Glory Cloud.
Right.
So God does dwell there but he
he keeps himself detached from
from the physical building.
He says I'm not only going to be
here and I'm not always going to
be here.
Right.
But I will, I will God to set to be here.
And the reason for that, the reason for that
is part of the way temples functioned in the pagan world.
We've talked a lot about in idolatry,
how the idol became a body of the God,
a hypostasis of the God.
But in many ways, they believed the temple building
Similarly was it self?
sort of a body of the God.
Yeah, and I was just gonna say,
for those who are kind of wanting to look up exactly
the stuff that we just talked about,
that's in second Chronicles chapter six.
You can see the prayer of dedication
and the God's response and all that kind of stuff is there.
Yeah, it's also in the first cakes.
Yeah, okay.
But,
so,
the
once once you
have that idea right that the temple itself is sort of seen and utilized the way an idol is
then the way Solomon was talking right kind of makes sense right we talked about how the idol
is sort of this point of leverage right and so the temple building itself could be such a point
of leverage right a god trap as it were right and not just the building the building of it
let's see it is doing something for you know I've made a house for you I've made a place for you
to live. I'm your landlord.
Yeah, right.
And it was seen to sort of impose like an obligation, right?
So for example, when Arminius, not that one, the German general defeated the Roman legions
in Germany, there was a period of time where the Romans would go and throw rocks at the
The temples, and throw curses at them.
Right?
because they were saying we built you these beautiful temples and we offered you all these sacrifices,
gods, and you didn't you blew it.
Yeah.
So there are army lost.
They see it as hurting gods by throwing rocks at their temples.
Right.
So it's sort of like, uh, bombs, you know, like what the Yankees lose, you know, everybody.
The worthless ones to make a call to one of our previous, yeah.
So, uh...
And you see this reflected not only in Solomon's prayer, but in the design because he basically built a Phoenician temple.
Right. One of the features, for example, is the two pillars, the two prominent pillars at the front made of different materials.
And those pillars are, I mean everybody argues about this, right?
Because, you know, journal articles and dissertations have to be written.
But one common way of viewing what's going on
with the two pillars and infanation temples
made of these two different materials
is that they represent sort of the carotid in the jugular.
So the idea being that the temple building
is sort of the God's heart.
Yeah, and for those of you who've been a long time
since you studied any anatomy or whatever,
That's the two and from passages to the human heart.
Well, from the heart to the brain.
Yeah, the heart to the brain, sorry.
Yeah, through your neck.
Yeah, right.
Which if you cut your dead.
Yeah.
So don't do that, everyone.
Yes.
Yeah.
That's the pastoral application of what we're just saying.
Yes.
So that's sort of the vital, right?
Like the vital power.
Right.
This is the sort of divine life imbued into this building.
And you see this, this view was...
sort of, is this just sort of Solomon yielding to paganism as he was want. But this is
carried on in Judah all the way to the end, because this is one of the problems Jeremiah has,
right? So there's a whole bunch of people, Jeremiah is coming and giving these prophecies of doom
and destruction and everybody's calling them a false prophet and saying these other prophets who
where the actual false prophets...
were saying, no, everything's good. The peace piece, but there is no peace folks. Right?
These are the real prophets and part of their evidence was, well, look, you always temples
here. You can't let anything happen to his temple. Right? So like the building itself
is a sort of magical talisman, right? That God is somehow bound to. Right? And we all
know of course that the God of Israel's response to that was nope.
but he was perfectly capable of leaving.
But that was their idea.
Now this idea of the temple as body of God gets repurposed in Ezekiel.
Yeah, he read, I don't know, he read Conzi on some level, right?
Right. He takes it and adverts it a little bit, right?
Because here's one of the interesting things, right?
and sorry dispensationalists, but...
Yeah, let's talk to the dispensationalists.
Okay.
Dispensationalists sit down.
Our dispensationalist friends, right?
Oh no, I want them friends.
Or what?
Or what to point out that, that, that the temple,
those are the days of Ezra and Nehemiah.
The temple redebocated by the back of bees.
Herod's temple none of the
those temples match the description of the temple in a zeheal.
Right. They point that out. Right. Right.
But then they conclude from that that well that must be that a temple exactly matching this is going to be built.
Sometime in the future. Right. Yeah.
The end times within a generation of 1948 oops never mind that part.
Right.
So.
Here's the
The problem with that is that if the original here is of Ezekiel's
prophecy, right, Ezekiel's in the exile, right, if the original
here is interpreted this literally in that sense, right, this is going to be the
measurements, et cetera, of the temple of the future, why didn't they rebuild it
that way?
Yeah, they built something else.
They built something else.
Why didn't the Maccabees, they re-dedicated it, built it that way.
Herod's construction was actually more elaborate in a lot of ways.
Right.
And more difficult.
Herod was aware of the book of Ezekiel.
Sure.
Right.
And the sanctuaries who were running the temple were intimately aware of it.
That's why they called themselves Zatakites.
Right.
the cast of the
themselves as those future priests. Why did they want the temple to match? Right? Because
none of them read it that way. Right. Right. Right. This is why we have to say sorry,
dispensationalists. None of them read it that way. And none of the early Christians read it that way.
Right. Yeah. You don't find anywhere early Christians saying, okay now we need to we need to build
a temple that matches this description in Ezekiel. No. You find quite the opposite. The only people you
you find talking about the Jewish temple again.
rebuilds or people saying the Antichrist is going to do it. Yeah. And that's mostly after
Julian, the apostate tried to do it because, you know, they said, Julian, the apostate, he's
kind of an Antichrist. But the point being, right, that the original Jewish here, so second
temple Judaism, right, where should we get a temple that didn't match this one? Red this
typologically right
they thought that this description of the temple was conveying certain truths. They didn't read it as there's going to someday be a physical building that batches this.
Right.
And so those typological readings sort of found their end and found their fulfillment among early Christians who read this as read this typologically but referring to Christ.
Yeah, not to a building.
So this temple is the body of God because it's Christ.
because it's Christ.
Yeah.
Christ's body, right?
And so, and when I say early Christians, I mean like, for example, St. John the Evangelist.
Right.
Yeah, because Christ himself says, you know, he refers to his, and John supplies his
deportation.
Yes.
You know, you're going to, you know, you'll tear down this temple and, you know, and
then I will raise it again in three days, and then it says, and by this, he meant his
body.
Yes.
good about the parenthetical notes just in case you're not track
Okay.
All right.
Thank you.
Thank you, sir.
Yes.
Right.
So yeah.
So there's other problems with getting back to Solomon's temple.
There's other problems with it.
Like big, big problems, right?
Right.
Well, yeah.
Yeah.
So we talked about paganism as what Solomon's want.
I mean, we all know this is why he ended up losing his kingdom.
Right.
It's because he didn't just build this temple.
He built a lot more to other gods from his other wives, right?
But even this temple, he didn't do so well. It's not just that, oh yeah, he had the temple of Yahweh, the God of Israel, and then he had a bail temple down the street, and then he added Egyptian temple down the street from that.
He even messed up with this one. So this is a tale of two chariots.
Okay, right? So if you go back to first Chronicles 28 and you read verse 18, it talks about how
part of David's idea was to have sort of a chariot throne surrounding the Ark of the
Covenant within the Holy of Holies, within the permanent building.
And this was there. This was built and one was built in the second temple too by the way.
Even though they didn't have the Ark of the Covenant, they still had the big cherubum
throw back there. Right. Um, with where it should would have been.
right. And those cherubim by the way for interested people once that when when the Romans destroyed
the temple in 8070 which sorry, Preterus was actually not that big of a deal. But anyway,
when when they destroyed the temple in 8070, those cherubim were taken to Antioch.
Those huge chairs for the table because
because any of-
was the second largest Jewish population in the world at the time. So it was kind of rubbing
it in their faces. Yes, they were put on display there, both to rub it in their face, and they
wanted to prevent that Jewish community from revolting the way Jerusalem had. Right? Romans were
we're going to object lessons. So, but now, so this this chariot throw.
Right. Representing the throne of Yahweh, the God of Israel. Who got to see that?
Just the high priest once a year through a haze of incense smoke. On the David's own man, right?
On the David's own, but so he wouldn't die. Okay. But Solomon also built another
chariot. Yes. And we find out that Solomon built this in 2nd Kings 23 verse 11.
Cherry, it's a fire, right?
Eh, he's sort of...
Yeah. Sorry. And this was we mentioned this briefly back in the Melchizedek episode, right?
That the pagan god who was worshiped at Jerusalem,
Jerusalem, before David took it, was Cedicah, who is a, or Cedic, who is, was seen as a
a hypostasis of shimmy.
There's a sun god. So Shemus Zeneca, the son of righteousness. This is why Christ is referred to in our liturgy.
It says the true son of righteousness over against this fake one. But so Shemus Zeneca, the sun god, wrote in a chariot,
and Solomon built one for him and put it at the entrance to the temple in Jerusalem. And it was there from his time
when the temple was first built all the way through the history of Judah to King Josiah's
reforms. King Josiah destroyed it and that was about 25 years before the fall of Jerusalem to the
Babylonians. So for pretty much the entirety of the history of Judah, people who actually came
to the temple to worship. Now given the whole northern kingdom isn't going to the temple to
there at that
going to the Golden Caves at Bethel and Dan. But those who are actually going
to the temple to worship, what are they seeing and interacting with? Yeah. The
chariot of Shemish Zedaka because they don't go in. Yeah. They're there with the
idol for the whole history of Judah. Yeah. Centuries. Right. I think what
a couple hundred years or so right?
Yeah more than that.
Yeah about three.
pretty fitting. Oh really? Oh wow. Yeah. So yeah. So this is, this is another piece of that.
Once again, you know, you, you get all these shocking documentaries, right? Where scholars,
you know, nice, nice seeming Greek ladies with British accents. Come on and tell you,
I'm not referring to anyone in particular, I promise.
That the Bible tells you.
that ancient Israel was monotheistic, but it's lie. They were really polytheistic pagans.
Yeah, because. And you go, we read the Bible. Yeah, right. Yeah, exactly. Exactly.
Right. It's like, yes, they were. The question is not, did the ancient Israelites worship
more than one God? Right. The question is, were they supposed to? Right. And that's the question.
and notably
If you read the scriptures closely,
or not even that closely, frankly,
if you just simply read the scriptures,
you see they present God
punishing them for doing this,
God condemning them for doing this,
allowing invasions,
all this kind of stuff over and over and over again.
And so it's an interesting question then,
if ancient Israel was actually totally cool
cool with being polytheistic.
if everyone's been lying to you, right?
It's like, well, why would they preserve the scriptures
in this way?
If there's not the...
Say the opposite.
Yeah, that's actually the opposite,
that point out how bad they are.
And to me, actually, this is another of these things,
like, for instance, the apostles recording their own stupid
sayings and sins and betrayals in the gospels
that is an indication of the truth of a lot of this.
It's that, you know, if it's all just propaganda,
Why would you depict your
leaders and forebears and whatever in this bad light, you know, but but there it is. There it is.
You know, this is this is God's opinion about all these things is what the scriptures is so. Yeah, so right, right. And that's
um yeah, and so the thing here is God of course knew what would happen when they allowed their
are related to put down roots.
Form these permanent insides.
institutions, they would start to become deformed.
Right?
By keeping the tabernacle, by keeping them unruited, right?
By a Saint Peter would later say,
us continuing to live as aliens and strangers in the world, right?
The way Abraham lived is opposed to a lot who went to go live in Sodom, right?
That that would help preserve, right, the reality of who God is,
is rather than having it be deformed as they've as they
And so this sort of thing that happened is exactly why God did not want that permanent temple in the first place.
All right, well we're going to take another quick break and we'll be right back with the third half of the Lord of Spirits.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call.
the third half of the Lord of Spirits.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymick and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls
on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call.
call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Are you curious about the Orthodox Christian faith?
Do you have questions about Orthodox Christianity
that you can't trust strangers and internet forums to answer?
Are you an Orthodox Christian looking
for a reliable first place to send...
your interested friends. Do you need help finding an Orthodox Church near you?
My name is Father Paul Hodge. I serve in the Antiochian Orthodox Christian Archdiocese of North
America. My name is Father Joseph Lucas. I serve in the Orthodox Church in America.
My name is Father Anthony Cook. I serve in the Greek Orthodox Archdiocese of America.
And I'm Father Andrew Stephen Damick, Chief Content Officer of Ancient Faith Ministries
and a priest of the Antioch Narcissus. And where the orthodox in
If you're looking for a first stop online to get an introduction to the Orthodox faith,
a place to get answers to questions from qualified Orthodox Christian clergy,
a place to send your friends and not just toss them into the chaos of the Internet,
a place to get help finding an Orthodox parish and get plugged into an actual Orthodox community,
then point your web browser at orthroxintro.org.
orthodoxintro.org is a free service of ancient faith ministries
and made possible by our donors.
It's an Orthodox Onramp to the Christian life.
Again, that's Orthodoxintro.org.
[♪ OUTRO MUSIC PLAYING [♪
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 8558
All right, welcome back. It's the third half of the Lord of Spirits podcast because this
is a podcast and a half. And once again, you can't call in despite what the voice of Steve
just said to you. Well, you can. You can. That's true. You'll not get the very kind voice
of Matroska Trudy on the other end.
listening to whatever it is you have to say to her and trying to pass that on to us.
You're not going to get that this time around.
So it's okay.
Yes.
It's all right.
We're here for you.
Just not just not live.
When we do this, when we do this and we're not live,
what we need to do is we need to find recordings of one of those old 976 numbers.
Like that would tell you scary stories that Halloween or something or the one that did Bible stories.
Wow.
That does take me back.
and just took that up to the to the
So that if anybody calls in during a non-life show, they get that.
That's a great idea. And I'm sure we can find a donor to cover that. No. Yeah. Yeah.
So all right. Well, we just finished up the second half talking about the Tabernacle and its actual contents.
And so forth is structured contents. And we talked about the Temple of Solomon and how that really was not what God had in mind.
Uh oh bad.
Yeah, yeah, very bad.
Just not not not good, not good.
So here in the third half now,
we're gonna talk about how the tabernacle
is understood in the new testament.
So.
Oh, one more note though, I'll solve it.
Sure, yeah.
I want to get tried to preclude a certain number
of emails that I'll have to skim.
And that is that somebody will say,
actually Solomon's a saint.
Okay.
So here's the thing.
So I'm ready.
Solomon, in terms of the story of Solomon in first gigs that did Chronicles is presented
to sort of the prototypical like reprobate, right?
Yeah.
But, but within the tradition of the church, Solomon, the figure of Solomon includes cohella
at the teacher of ecclesiastes.
right? And not going to sit here and argue because that's a show and a half all by itself,
the authorship of Ecclesiastes when it was written and all that. The point though being Ecclesiastes
is taken to represent the fact that late in his life Solomon found repentance. There you go.
Right? That works out. And so this is why this is why Solomon is not considered a righteous king.
by the Old Testament.
And usually most icons of the resurrection, for example,
just have King's David and Josiah as the righteous.
But that repentance, you can sit in mindily and still be
a saint if you repent mindily.
And that's what's going on there.
So thank you for that.
Yes, now I want to have to skim those emails.
Right.
I'm sure there's a bunch of people that drop out
sometime in the middle of the second half.
So maybe you will.
Who will send those emails?
Yeah, yeah.
Or we're typing it like during the half, yeah.
And already hit send.
No, now we'll get the emails about,
what are you saying about Ecclesiastes?
But in any rate, yes.
So the tabernacle in the New Testament.
Right.
Well, that's so this is...
This is important because that idea that the temple wasn't all that hot, right?
In the Old Testament is further born out in the New Testament.
Right.
And also why, as you mentioned, the destruction of the temple by the Romans is not
really considered a significant Christian event.
Right.
It's not as big of a deal as the Presbyterians want it to be.
Yes.
Right.
So,
All right.
And so part of how we see that is that in the New Testament, when we see reflections on both
heavenly worship and Christian worship, we see people talking in terms of the tabernacle and not
the temple. Right. Right. And this begins to be telegraphed even in the attitude we see sort of
Bord Herod's temple expressed in the Gospels,
the kind of ambivalent attitude in the Gospel and Acts.
I say ambivalent, right?
Both sides, right?
So on one hand, it's not outright rejected.
Right.
Right by Christ or by the apostles.
But it's not fully embraced either, right?
No, there's no commandments by them to go to the temple
and do X, Y and Z.
We read them doing that.
But again, it seems to be sort of a voluntary association kind of thing, right?
So and this is not
sort of some kind of radical this ambivalence is not sort of a radical thing in the New Testament.
This is pretty common in the Judaism's of the day, right?
So there are lots of forms of Judaism in the second temple period that have varying relationships with
with the Temple of Jerusalem, Herod's
temple in particular at that time.
So there are groups like the group at Kumaran,
wrote the Densy Scrolls, who rejected Herod's temple
completely.
Right.
And they were doing some kind of rituals out there
in the desert to replace it, is that the idea?
Right.
Yeah.
They had taken certain elements of temple ritual,
minus the offering of sacrifices, for example.
we're recreating those at
at cumeron, right? But they rejected here. There's a couple outright. There were other groups
similarly. What you see with the Pharisees is a similar kind of ambivalence, right? So
recognition that, yeah, this is the temple, but also the recognition that there's something
very wrong. The key signifier of the something wrong, being not just the association with
Herod who's...
you know, not Jewish. But the mean. But that the fioffatic glory cloud, the presence of God never
returns to the temple after it's rebuilt. Right. That being the key major signifier that something's
wrong with it, right? So then you get this ambivalence. Yeah, so there's a sense of, okay, well
So God did not come and visually dissa...
center of the temple, we're gonna still use it to worship him because we got to worship him.
So okay, we'll get what else do you have? Yeah, right, right, right? Yeah.
So, and then there's lots of debate as to, right? So at Kumbhra, they think that's not correctable.
Right. The Pharisees kind of thought that was potentially correctable.
Yeah, but everybody keeping the law perfectly right keeping the keeping the tour
returning to the Torah, getting rid of those no good Sadducees, right?
Returning it to the rightful people that when all that happened, then God's
presence would return and then things would be right.
Right.
And that was associated with the coming of the Messiah and all of those things, right?
So but there's already also a running theme in the Old Testament that really comes to
flower in the Gospels.
that at a variety of times, in a variety of periods,
God sort of disassociates himself at his presence,
at his name, from the temple,
sometime at least once, even from the tabernacle.
And that presence is then located
by means of his spirit in dwelling
some person or persons.
Right. So, one of the first examples of this that we see is actually in first Samuel,
and it's in the person of the prophet Samuel, who in the early chapters of Samuel, we see,
you know, Eli and his sons, that the priesthood that's associated with the tabernacle is corrupted.
Right. Right. And we then read about, and people may not even pause to think about it,
Samuel sets up his own altar.
Not at the tabernacle.
Yeah. And offer sacrifices to God there at a debauch.
That's a that's a big statement.
Yeah.
Where he has a community of prophets living around him.
This kind of proto-monastic right city of prophets.
That's where Saul goes to and Rips off all his clothes and flops around on the ground.
Um, um,
as we've previously said.
Yeah.
When the spirit sees this, everybody prophesies.
But the point being,
I was just say kind of Israel and exile is sort of the idea,
you know, like a government and exile, right?
Right, right.
That God's presence has left sort of the official nostalgia
and has gone there, right?
You're gonna see shades of this in,
say to me, the Newfield Ocean, by the way.
A couple thousand years later.
But, so that happens,
this happens more than once, right? We have this thing that looks like a weird detour in the books
of First and Second Kings, which ostensibly are about the kings, right? We're going down through
the kingly lines describing what the kings did, mostly how wicked they were, and then all of a sudden
we follow the prophets Elijah and Elijah for a long time. Who are not down in Judah? Yeah,
And we're not kings.
Yeah, right.
Yeah.
Right.
That's all this up now. We're following that. Why? Well, because especially when you're dealing with you know, A have it at at Jezebel and their priests and yeah, and the the religion of the Northern Kingdom and the Golden Caves at Bethel and Dan, right?
That's not the king and the priest is not the place where God's presence is, right?
His presence was never at the shrines at Beppel and Dan, right?
So no, it's with these prophets. We're in dwelt by the Spirit.
of God. See the same thing with Jeremiah as we alluded to earlier, right? They're putting
all their confidence of the fact that this building is here, right? But God has sort
of left the building. It is now His spirit is dwelling in Jeremiah, right? And Jeremiah
is now the focus of God's activity, right, among, among His people. And then when we get
into the New Testament then, we see this particularly in St. Luke's Gospel with
Saint John the four runner whose father is a priest right right in the temple in Jerusalem
right and who then gets killed and who you know for a while his voice falls silent which is a kind
of literal muting of the priesthood yeah yeah and then where does where does God's presence go it goes
out into the wilderness with St. John.
Right, the word of the Lord.
comes to St. John and the wilderness.
Yeah, it's not at the temple.
Right? It's now with St. John and the wilderness,
where he's bringing together the faithful remnant,
right, and gathering these disciples,
who he then turns over to Christ,
who, as we already talked about,
St. John points out, is now the temple.
Yep, including my patron saint.
Right. He goes from St. John to the work.
Yeah, yeah.
And so
This idea, right, from the beginning, really, from God's ambivalent statement at the time he comes to dwell in Solomon's temple.
There is this idea that God isn't sort of permanently attached to this building.
And that this building is at a condescension, and that it's always problematic.
And so this this detachment from the bill.
you know, Ezekiel sees him leave the building, right?
There's firm precedent and idea for it.
And so, when by the time that temple is destroyed in AD 70, right,
the reason you don't see anything about it anywhere in the New Testament is
because it wasn't a big deal at that point for Christians.
Yeah, because it happens within the scope of the timeline of the New Testament.
Right.
Right, they didn't need it anymore.
more. Not even mentioned, right? Not even mentioned. And, right. And so again, sorry,
Presbyterians, but a much bigger deal historically, and this is, I'll just note this once again
for Preterus. If you really want to be a Preterus, why not AD 135? Jerusalem gets destroyed.
There's a false Messiah who everybody follows, like all the stuff is there. Anyway, moving
Oh, God.
For picking up.
on printers. And this really comes to fruition, right? When you look at the end of the book of
Revelation, you look at the New Heavens of the Earth and it's explicit, there's no temple.
Right? There's no temple. Yeah. Go ahead. Yeah. Go ahead. I was going to say, I mean,
yeah, what you see in, maybe I'm just going to state what you're about to say. What you see in
Revelation 15 with John the Evangelist sees worship in heaven.
and is not a temple.
It's the tabernacle.
Yeah, literally.
Yeah, yeah.
It's always a tent.
Worship and heaven always happens in a tent.
Right, right.
It's not just that we're saying,
oh look, it's the incense offering
that happened in the tent, right?
If you read Revelation 15, 5 through 8, right?
It says tent.
Yeah, exactly.
Exactly.
So okay, so we're gonna read that to you
so you can just hear it.
This is Revelation 5.
Starting with verse 15, verse 15, verse 15, verse 5, verse 8.
After this I looked, and the sanctuary of the tent of witness in heaven was opened.
And out of the sanctuary came the seven angels with the seven plagues, clothed in pure bright linen with golden sashes around their chests.
And one of the four living creatures gave to the seven angels seven golden bulls full of the wrath of God who lives forever and ever.
And the sanctuary with...
filled with smoke from the glory of God and from his power, and no one could enter the sanctuary
until the seven plagues of the seven angels were finished. Right, so they come out of the tent,
that's the heavenly tent, the one that Moses went into that the earthly one was patterned after.
Yeah, right? Yeah, and it's and it's notable what it says there at the end of verse eight that no
No one could enter the sanctuary until the seven plagues of the seven angels were finished.
I mean, what are the seven plagues?
It's them bringing out this incense, this wrath incense that brings the plagues, but, you
know, knowing what, you know, listener, if you're, if you remember what we said about
these things coming out of the holy place in the tabernacle, the point is to enable entrance
as no one could enter the sanctuary until.
So the plagues are this kind of incense of purification that's being enacted as
logically so that people can enter into the Holy of Holies.
Right, right.
So purify the earth so that it can become the sanctuary.
Yeah.
And of course, as we already saw in Hebrews and read,
Christ is the high priest.
Where does he service high priest?
In the tent, right?
In the tabernacle.
Not in a temple.
Yeah.
So with that in mind.
as one might expect, when we see early orthodox Christian worship spaces, right, and even contemporary ones,
they're patterned after the tabernacle.
Yeah, I mean, we often call them temples because there is a permanence to them and they're made of stone and so forth.
But their pattern is not after, like Solomon's temple or Herod's temple, right?
Right. Yeah, yeah, it's after the
We don't have any sun god chariots.
Yeah, thank you.
No Sun god chariots.
No chance that your offering is sacrifice.
Casually, a Christmas tree stir the pot.
So we can be, we can even written right now.
Oh, yeah, oh, yeah.
So, what's again, in talking about right in the next
Christian Wart space, we can sort of start at the outer court
and work our way in.
That's like you do the tabernacle.
Yes.
So, if you read those great old King James influence translations of our baptismal liturgics
are quast and talking about baptism in the church fathers, you find it referred to as the
labor of regeneration.
Right.
And where does baptism normally happen in the narthex or sometimes a separate building
that's kind of near the entrance.
But in the narthics is where baptism traditionally happens.
Right. And so this is for entrance and it's the labor of regeneration because, again,
this fulfillment idea, right, filled up to overflowing. It's not just washing your hands and
washing your feet. Right. And having to do that over and over and over and over and over
again, right? But this is something that happens once for the purification of soul and body.
Right. Right. And then you also have sort of branching out
washings that still do occur that are
sort of related to this by being a renewal of baptism.
So for instance, the clergy, right, when they're done
vesting, they wash their hands.
But only when they're done vesting to serve the divine
liturgy, right? It's for the the Eucharist is when they do
this hand washing. And then there's also the bishop.
Oh yeah, the bishop ceremony. Exactly. Yeah, exactly during the
hierarchical liturgy, which where that happens right before
the great entrance of the gifts. Right. Yeah. Because he's a
you
He's about to receive the gifts is what's going on.
That's why his hands are being washed
because they're about to be handed to him
after the entrance is done.
And then, you know, for every Christian,
there's the tears of repentance that happen in confession,
which are understood and very explicitly said,
in many cases, as a renewal of baptism.
And what is one of the reasons you're going to confession?
It's precisely to purify you
so that you can then participate in the sacrifice
of the Eucharist.
So again, you see this washing.
is about being able to enter in
participate. Right. Being able to enter it, right? Because, of
course, as we said before, the place where we are, where the
people are during the service is the holy place. Right. Right.
You're not now outside the building. Yeah, we've entered into
the tent. Right. We've entered into the tent. That's what the
the the the name of the church is. Right. So you're at the place
with a priest. Right, where?
We talked about our episode about priesthood.
But so then what's what's the other element that was in the outer court that was related to entrance?
That was the altar of burnt offering. Yep, right?
So that purification of sin restoration of communion the building of communion with God, right?
Which is also right your your baptized
for the remission of sins that's renewed in confession and
and, uh, and absolution, right?
And there is.
I'd say there is even a not everywhere does this, but when the tonsure of the hair of the head
is done at baptism, in some cases it's placed onto the sensor and burnt up as a kind of offering
to God. I mean, there's various things that are done with the hair in different traditions,
but that's one of them. That's one possibility. Yeah. So, yeah, and so this also is related to entrance
and the quenzy.
and purification of sins. And this is why traditionally, if we go back to the early church,
unbaptized people, right, and people who were penitents, people who were repenting, but
had not yet done the things they needed to do to receive absolution, right. Because
Sometimes it's easier to send than it is to repair the damage we do when we send.
Pretty much almost.
Yes.
Yeah.
You know, that's why people sin.
You don't have to go way out of your way.
Right.
Those folks would be for a time would be penitence, right?
And wouldn't be.
Is it just that they couldn't receive the Eucharist, but they were.
Traditionally, they were kept outside in the equivalent of the narthex.
Right.
during that time they could
enter in, enter in yet. So that idea is still preserved there, but that's not the focus, right?
The focus, and this tends to be especially non-orthodox people hearing us, right? They tend to look
at the Orthodox Church and focus on exclusion, right? Like you're saying I can't come receive communion
at your church. You're saying I shouldn't even walk in now. Right? Right? No, the point is the
The way is open and here's how you walk the way.
And if you don't want to do that, that's your choice.
You've chosen not to do that, but the way is open.
There's no one that's ever excluded for their whole lives and no matter what from the
church.
There's always a way.
They have to be willing to walk the way.
But there's always a way.
Right.
like if we think about it and the terms we're talking about it now, that especially-
it doesn't make sense, right? So at the tabernacle, the labor and the alter of
burn offering, we're not there to exclude people. Right. They're the exact opposite.
Preparing them to come in. Right. They're the means by which you can be included.
Do the means of entry. Decontaminations to be put in and start directors. Right.
So cataclysis and baptism and repentance and all these things, these are the means of entering.
These are not.
barriers of exclusion. Right. Right. Right. So then we go to the Tabernacle, right, into the tent,
right, the holy place and the most holy place, right. And, you know, sort of the basic daily cycle,
and we've said this before I know, of the Orthodox Church, is Vespers and Mattins, right? The
kindling of the lamps and the trimming of the lamps.
right? That's where incense is offered with prayer, right? At sunrise and sunset, right?
This is first commandment about worship in the Torah, right? And to prove that I'm not totally
unfriendly to the Presbyterians, hey, we should worship God the way he told us to by offering
him incense at morning and evening.
Lighted up Presbyterians.
Yeah.
So.
Um.
So we see that pattern. We have the lampstand on the altar with the seven branches.
And you see the importance of that in the letters to the seven churches of the book of Revelation.
Right where you've got the lampstand is lit as an earmark of the local church existing as the
church and if they get the
that Lampstand gets removed, then that means that's not really the church anymore.
Right, the phrase, the Lampstand will be removed and because it was written after the destruction of the temple,
where the Archivist had that image of the Lampstand being removed for the Jerusalem temple and the Laga Fruching of Temple.
That connects both every individual church as church, as worship space, as microcosm,
place where God is present.
but also the reality of it being taken away, right, was something that had happened, right, in Jerusalem.
Right, and so it functions in the same way. Right, remember the lampstand, the seven lights, right, this is the microcosm.
Some churches even have sort of like light blue ceilings, right?
In the buildings, right?
And you have the dome depicting Christ
and thrown in the heaven.
Yeah, and there's sometimes stars up there as well in the shadow of the years. Yeah. Yeah. And so the idea is that
as the place of worship liturgically, just like the tabernacle, it becomes a microcosm of
the entire creation. And just as the bread of the presence was there to feed the priests during their service,
Right? We're now all in that priest position.
And so we have
if you go to a divine literature, we have the antideron.
If you go to a visual service, right, or just a a
Vespa service where there's the Latia and Art of
Clasia, right, there is bread, right? And the point of that
bread is, I mean, is you're going to be in an all night
vigil? Is the original liturgical purpose of it? So it's
like here, you're going to need something to eat.
It's strengthening you for the time of your service. Exactly.
It's exactly the same purpose.
Yeah.
Right? It's God feeding His people, right? And strengthening them.
And we're all in there, sort of, so we all get it. It's not just about whatever priest
happens to be chosen by a lot to serve on that day. Right?
And then of course, on our altar table, right? Remember what we had in the, the Holy
of Holies, unless you're Ethiopian, you don't actually have an Ark of the Covenant there.
Right. But if you're Ethiopian, you kind of do.
Great.
But we have, right?
So there's a middle step, right?
Remember we had, and the arc was taken in procession.
We had the two tablets of the covenant.
By the time you get to synagogue worship, right?
You have the procession with the Torah scroll, right?
And on our altar tables, we have the gospel book, right?
And that is resident there at Christ.
the footstool, right, as the new covenant.
And we have the cross, right,
and usually the cross is a, in Eastern churches,
Eastern right churches at least, is usually a budding cross,
in for it's a callback, again, because erud's rod,
budded, right, life came out from it, right.
Um, um,
And our hemnography has explicit comparisons of the cross,
Aaron's rod that was forth with new life.
Right.
And we keep in what is called the tabernacle,
the altar, the Eucharist.
Right?
Exactly.
Because as Christ said, he's the bread
that came down from heaven.
Yeah.
I mean, talking about mana.
Just on the other side.
Outright says that.
Right.
I am, yeah.
Exactly.
Right.
And so, uh...
We have this actual space that is sacred space,
at which contains these objects, these items,
which are holy and sacred objects.
And this concept, we've broached this a few times
before in different ways, but this concept,
I know is difficult for sort of modern materialist
kind of.
folks, right? And some of those folks, right, sometimes will try to enlist certain things
said by St. Paul to argue against the idea of sacred particular sacred objects and particular
sacred spaces, and to sort of argue that every day is exactly the same.
Yeah, okay, so the passages that they would use for that
that there's Romans 14, 5, in which St. Paul says,
one person esteems one day as better than another.
While another esteems all days alike,
each one should be fully convinced in his own mind.
And so people look at that and say,
well, St. Paul is basically saying that feast days
are not a thing.
It should not be a thing, right?
That's the way that that gets read.
And then similarly, Colossians 2, 16, and 17,
therefore let no one pass judgment on you
questions of food and drink.
or with regard to a festival, or a new moon or a Sabbath,
these are a shadow of the things to come,
but the substance belongs to Christ.
And so then the interpretation would be,
all of those feast days and stuff,
we had the Old Testament, those were just a shadow,
and that's over now.
So we don't do that anymore.
There's no more feast days, you know,
because now we're Christians that Christ has come.
So that's kind of the reading of those two verses
in that context, yeah.
Right. So there aren't sacred times,
there aren't sacred places,
is there aren't sacred-
objects, right? Everything's the same. It's just material, right? And that
resonates very well with our modern secular culture. Right. But, but is not what
St. Paul is saying, right? Because the, as I was going to say, end is not what you
actually see early Christians doing. Right. Right. Right. So the idea of that
reading would then be this.
that when St. Paul says, you know, treat every day the same,
or treat every object, treat every place the same,
what he means is that you shouldn't honor the Sabbath.
Yeah, he's not saying that.
You shouldn't treat a church building as a sacred place,
or the temple in Jerusalem say that St. Paul used to visit.
Right.
I mean, I was going to say the problem,
the problem is that, you know, often what people say
is what everything is holy.
And but the problem is
than when people say that what they mean by it in terms of actual practical application
is that nothing is holy.
Right.
If everybody is special, nobody is special.
Sorry, millennials.
That was a cheap shot.
Even I think that wasn't you.
Wow.
I know you treasure your participation trophies.
It's okay.
What?
You know, this is like 50% of our audience, right?
I know.
Bye bye.
control. He's a wild man. I can't stop him everybody. That's a stereotype. But no, but yeah, so yeah,
if everything is special, nothing is special. Right. If everything is great, nothing is great. Right.
Right. And so St. Paul wasn't saying either of those things. He wasn't saying nothing is sacred,
and he wasn't saying everything is sacred.
He's saying everything is potentially sacred.
Mm.
Every space is potentially sacred space.
Every time is potentially sacred time.
Every object is potentially a sacred object.
It has that potential.
So the person who treats every day the same
is the person who is able to treat every day like the Sabbath.
The person who treats his home as just as holy as the church
doesn't do that by degrading how he treats the church.
but she does that by elevating how he treats his hope.
right, to being a small church, right?
So that's what St. Paul is getting out there, right?
And so we have particular sacred times and sacred places and sacred objects to teach us how to do that.
So if we learn how to respect our church sanctuary,
then that teaches us how to treat a place
as holy and we can then apply that to other places. Right? And likewise with objects with things,
right? Times. And so he's pointing to that potential, not a reality on either side.
Well, and even again, you know, when we see worship conducted in heaven, there is still this kind of
of demarcation of spaces going on.
You know, there's play, there is a holiest place that
things are coming out from.
Right.
So, I mean, it's not by any means saying that the age to come,
that the kingdom of God is unholy in any way,
but there is clearly still a hierarchy within it.
You know, that's still happening.
There's still spaces that are kind of better than others
in that sense.
Well, or different.
Or different eggs.
I set up side for particular purpose.
Yes, yeah, I think that's one of the things.
You could tell it just by the way I said that.
I think that's one of the things that...
A lot of modern people when they hear the word holy, what they understand by it is to
mean better than.
But it's interesting if you read, for instance, we've mentioned a lot of the laws and
stuff and excess and Leviticus and numbers, you'll hear this refrain over and over again
about something being sanctified, sanctified, sanctified, sanctified.
And it's very clear in context that what that means is set apart for a particular purpose.
there's some cases in which we're saying to
is used that it would not make any sense to mean something is better than or is kind of shining
with mystical light or whatever we mean by holy or sanctified, that it just means simply separated.
Separate it out. We've got Plato brain and so we bring like good and evil into our ontology
and stuff in weird ways, right?
So like we're human, okay?
We all have to go to the bathroom.
somewhere. We don't do that in a holy place. Right. Right. We do that in a place set aside for that purpose. Right. But the bathroom is not like evil. Right.
Right. Right. Right. It's a necessary thing before we get necessary function. And hopefully you keep it clean. And you don't put your eye on corner in there.
Right. You know, like that that's just not what you would do. Right. But it's not because it's evil. Right.
That's not...
But it's purpose.
Right.
So one of the things, though, with Christian worship spaces in particular, is that they have,
since the very beginning, been made holy, not just by this is the place we're going to
set aside for worship.
because they are built surrounding a particular thing.
And that is the relics of saints, originally specifically martyrs.
And this is something that a lot of our friends and
listeners probably are really uncomfortable with.
Even some of the Orthodox ones probably.
It's true. I mean, I get a little, right?
A little ugot. Yeah.
And, you know, like, how do we know that this was the case early, early on?
well there are
testimonies about worship happening in the catacombs in Rome and
What are catacombs? It's not just hidden away places. They specifically were performing the divine liturgy on top of the grave of a martyr who was buried down in there
Right, right, so that that is going on
Yeah
Saint Jerome just said is a summary statement the graves of the martyrs are altars to Christ
Right not that they make handy spots
Yeah, to do that.
where you should build one but they are. Yeah, by virtue of being the grave of a martyr,
it's an altar to Christ. Right. And that understanding develops out of what we've been talking about
in this third half, right, that what's serving now is a temple, right. When God separates himself from
from the building, right, for the tabernacle, for the temple, right. He comes to dwell within
in the saints, right?
The Holy Spirit.
that, Holy Spirit dwelling within Elijah,
Elijah, Samuel, St. John the Forerunner, right?
And so that is the place,
that is the place of God's presence.
And the righteous, right,
part of being a saint, part of being righteous, right?
Is that, as St. Paul says, you know,
you offer your members become the members of Christ,
Right.
As we just heard of the epistle.
yesterday as we're recording this. Our members become the members of Christ with the Holy Spirit
dwells within us, right? Our body becomes the body of Christ, right, through which he acts, meaning
body of God, right? That imaging, that imaging function, but that's transformative of the human
person. It doesn't just transform their soul and make their soul like an angel, right?
A soul is not a thing.
It's not a sphere like origin thought.
It's not this eternal immortal thing, right?
A soul is your life, right?
It's what makes your body alive.
And so when it leaves, when your life leaves the body,
the body dies, decomposes.
We believe our life is hidden with Christ
and Christ returns our life to the body, right?
But the body is still the person right so belongs to that person
I mean we you know for a lot more on this see our episodes about bodies and then also see our our episode about relics
We did all right and so
That is why that body of the saying is associated with a worship space, right? So a laisha
His body doesn't stop being that. That's why when they throw a quorum.
it was tomb, it rises from the dead.
And so Christians understood this innately
from the beginning and just started doing it.
And this became two pagans, outsiders.
This is what Christians did.
This is what Christians do.
Now, right now, if
I went to the average person in the US, Christian or not, right?
And I said, here's what Christians do.
They parade around with and pray at and offer sacrifices at the bodies of a bunch of dead people.
The average American, Christian or not would look at you like I was at SAID, right?
It'd be like, what?
I think I saw them doing some Catholics doing some stuff like that in Mexico.
What are you talking about?
Right? Like they would not, you know, right? I don't know how that at all. But what do we find in the fourth century?
When we look at what pagans said, Christianity was all about.
Right. So, so we've got, we've got a couple of quotes here.
And these are amazing. So one is from Julian the Apostate.
So he's not just some random pagan.
He's he's an ex-Christian. Yes, the nephew of Constantine. Yeah, bringing back and wasn't he a
like a classmate with, is it Greg or the Thalotian? Yeah, St. Basil. Yeah, so and you know, so he's
he becomes the emperor of Rome and he's trying to bring back paganism and he hates Christian.
And so he's going to say the worst possible things about it, but he's not going to say stuff that
that the people-
don't acknowledge as being true because they can see themselves what it is the Christians
are doing, and this is what Julian the Apostate said about what Christianity is about.
The carrying of the corpses of the dead through a great assembly of people in the midst of dense
crowds staining the eyesight of all with ill-ohmend sites of the dead, what day so touched with death
could be lucky. How after being present at such ceremonies could anyone approach the gods and
there
temples. So he's he's ridicule in
Christians and saying, look at what
they do. They carry their bones
of people around, you know, and
like, oh, yeah, it's a bad oh, man.
Yeah, it's so gross, you know, it
corrupts you right and and notice
Protestant friends. This is an
actual pagan. He doesn't say, oh,
all that saint stuff praying to
saints. That's just what we
pagans do. That's the same thing.
Yeah, he's saying, this is really
bad. He doesn't seem to think it's
to say pick it all.
Yeah, and he should know. Yeah, he would told he would totally know because he's Ben
Christian. He was raised Christian and then became pagan and favors paganism. Yeah, you know,
yeah. Okay, so we've got another one from Evnappius of Sardis, again from the fourth century.
He's pagan complaining about Christians. For they collected the bones and skulls of criminals,
who had been put to death for numerous crimes.
Made them out to be
gods and thought that they became better by defiling themselves at their graves.
Martyrs, the dead men were called and ministers of a sort and ambassadors with the gods to carry men's prayers.
So once again, and of course, you know, you see other elements in here, right?
Like, you know, of course, you're saying these are criminals.
Why are they venerated criminals?
You know, they were executed as criminals by the Roman government.
Right.
need them out to be gods.
Race.
So his understanding of Christianity
is that it's about theoses.
Thought that they became better
by defiling themselves at their graves.
He sees Christians making pilgrimage
to the graves of martyrs.
He calls the martyrs, they called martyrs,
the dead men were called,
and ministers, he sees them as priests
that the Christians are talking about them as priests,
and ambassadors with the gods to carry men's prayers
that people are addressing requests to these criminals.
and
the God and they're carrying them to God. So this is a pagan making fun of Christianity in
fourth century and he basically is talking about the veneration of the relics and the memories of
martyrs and the understanding that martyrs will pass on the prayers of Christians to God which I
mean we could just point out that we see that in the book of Revelation. But so yeah and it's
practically happening in the early church in this way.
Right, and is the common right this is what Christianity is about for and if not be this is not only
uh a pagan but he's a neoplateness. So he wrote the sort of biographies of famous philosophers basically
following neoplatism and it's actually one of the best sources on the lives of these philosophers.
So his text was actually preserved in the church, but he's
Constantly issuing anti-Christian attacks like this, right?
He hated Christianity.
And so St. Phoney is the great in the ninth century
said that he also had possession
in addition to the original of another version
of his writings that had all the anti-Christian stuff
edited out.
Because by that point everybody was a Christian, right?
And they were big fans.
But so notice folks who want to say
that, you know, oh, well, you know, the fourth century church, right, all those, all those
saints that counseled, I see it all that. They're just taking deoplatism and Greek philosophy
and distorting Christianity with it. Okay, this is a fourth century deoplateness,
did pagan. He doesn't think that we're doing the same thing. Right. And he should know. Yeah,
yeah, if anyone would know. Right. He thinks it's radically different. And it's interesting,
you know again you know part of what offends these papers.
in so much is this is kind of an inversion of pagan virtue, right?
Because it's humility and martyrdom that are elevated in Christianity.
Whereas for pagans that no, no, no, you know, paganism does not work that way.
That's why would you want to become like that person?
Yeah, like he's executed like a criminal.
Hello, total low life.
Yeah, right.
Yeah.
So this is, this is, yeah, they, they, and so they, they can't comprehend.
and not to mention, you know, they're not big fans of
the body in general. Right. Right. Right. It's all about escaping the body. Right. Remember,
St. Paul and Athens is going to laugh at what he talked about the resurrection. Right.
This is ridiculous to that. Right. So how much more triply ridiculous would it be to parade around
and honor some bones, right?
Like this, this makes zero, zero sense to them, right?
And so...
part of so that why, right, why, if this was the oppression on the ground at the time,
why do people today draw what seems to them to be easy connections between the veneration
of the saints and polytheism or between early Christian theology and neoplatonism, right?
If it was completely not obvious at the time, right? Why does it seem so?
And part of
it is because we've kind of got Protestant brain, even if we're not Protestants. And so we think of
Christianity as a set of beliefs. Right? We think of Christianity as a set of things that you hold
to be true, sort of logical propositions that you hold to be true. And so these comparisons are made
by, well, what is the veneration of saints? Well, it's a system of beliefs. Right? And so we line up
what those beliefs would be.
We then line up, well, what do pagan polytheists believe as if pagan religion had anything to do with quote-unquote beliefs
Right and believing in faith
Right there were no solar-feet-e-pagans. Okay. I assure you of that
Right and then we try to line up those beliefs and compare and contrast and they kind of look similar when we when we draw them out same thing with the
Oplatonism right
But that's not how neo-platonism or paganism or Christianity worked in the ancient world
They were...
not systems of belief.
There were ways of life that were made up of practices.
Yeah, and I mean, you can even see this,
like in the text of the ecumenical councils, right?
They have, certainly they have like statements of dogma,
but, you know, within all of that as well
as a huge amount of texts that are aimed at
the ways things are done, right?
It's not just, they're not just sort of regulatory,
I know sometimes we call them like disciplinary, whatever.
which is fine. I mean, I think that's an okay language, but we have to understand that
that this is so central that the ways things are done are so central that the the canonical
penalties that attach to them are things like being deposed from the priesthood or excommunication.
Right? You know, that's what's really attached. It's not just
here's some things that we say and everybody has to agree to this.
And indeed, what is a heretic according to an ecumenical counsel?
It's not just some...
who thinks certain things.
Has a bad idea.
Yeah. Is wrong.
Yeah. Yeah.
It's a teacher of those things.
In other words, you're teaching people to do and to say this other way.
Right.
Yeah. Yeah.
It's not thought crime.
There's no thought crime in an ecumenical council.
The original meaning of the word word heresy is a sect.
Right. Right.
It's an actual group.
Yes, your
a different group with a different way of life.
Because it's also isn't, it's not just that it's not beliefs,
it's not individual beliefs.
Right? We post-present Reformation,
the modern world, think of ourselves primarily as individuals.
Right? We're not talking about individuals.
We're talking about the way of life of a community.
The Christians in a city live their life
in a particular way as a community. Right?
That's what the pagan saw.
That's what in those quotes, they're critiquing.
They're not critiquing what individuals believe.
They're critiquing what the Christians as a community do.
How they conduct their life, how they worship, what they practice together.
Their way of life.
And so a heretic is someone, you know, like your archeretic, like areas or someone,
is someone who draws a following off after themselves and establishes another way of life.
Right and
another community. That's the problem, right? Just being in the church and being wrong about things, guess what? That's everybody. Right. We're all wrong in one way or another. Right.
None of us has perfect the ought most of us haven't even worked out most of us don't even have an opinion on most areas of theology. Right. I could find what obscure enough that you haven't even heard of. Right.
And you might be able to come up with that, but that's got nothing to do with what Christianity is.
right? That's sometimes how we teach it. That's sometimes how we do
catechesis even in the orthodox church. Right? Is I'm going to teach you a
bunch of things you should believe instead of the things you used to believe.
But that's not what Christianity is. Right? That's not what it and it's
definitely not what it was in the ancient world. Right? And so that's why we
get these kind of false results and see these false similarities. Right?
because the veneration of the saints is not a set of belief propositions.
positions. Right? It's it's something that was practiced by the earliest Christians. Right? It was observable
therefore. Right. By these by these outsiders. Yeah. And this really gets to this in particular gets to the core of what it means to believe in the resurrection of the dead. Right?
Because we tend to treat that as
Well, we believe that some day Jesus will return and everybody will be alive again in their body
Which is not wrong
Right, but right that is a true statement. Yeah, but and hopefully you hold to that because that's not even clear
With a lot of people unfortunately now in modern Christianity right a lot of people just talk about going to heaven forever and stuff which is not
It right
but
Believe in the resurrection goes.
goes a lot farther than that, right?
Because there's this element of resurrection
that we see in Christ's resurrection.
This gets brought out in Romans.
It gets brought out in the epistle of St. James
of vindication.
It's brought out in a lot of our orthodox himnography, right?
Christ died condemned as a criminal, right?
And when he rose from the dead,
that was the vindication of him.
of his claims to be the Messiah.
of his claims about who he was,
medication over against the slander
that was leveled against him by others
that ended in his death.
And this is true, as you can see in those quotes,
also of the martyrs, also of the righteous.
Right, they get just like Christ.
The righteous are persecuted, right?
The righteous suffer in this world.
The righteous are falsely accused.
the righteous, in the case of the martyrs,
were condemned to death as criminals.
And their resurrection is the vindication that no,
that's not who they are, because when Christ appears,
they appear with him, and they are still alive,
and they are reigning in glory with him.
All of this is entailed.
And Christ says as much when he critiques the Sadducees,
about the resurrection of the dead.
He doesn't say you're wrong.
On the last day, everyone is going to be raised from the dead bodily.
He says, God says, I am the God of Abraham, Isaac and Jacob.
He said that to Moses. Right?
He says God is not the God of the dead, but of the living.
So Christ's answer to what it means to believe in the resurrection of the dead
It means that you believe that those righteous are not dead.
are alive. Yeah. And what are they doing? Right? That they are with God, right? That they are
the pillars, right? So this idea of theosis of the saints, co-raining of them serving as priests,
ministers, and ambassadors, as our pagan friends, them serving as priests and co-rulers of Christ,
is if you don't have that, you don't really have belief in the
resurrection of the dead. Not in the sense that the scriptures mean it. Christ
just ambiguous that by Lazarus's grave. He says to Martha, do you believe in the
resurrection? She says, I believe that they only raised up on the last day.
Christ doesn't say right good. He says I am the resurrection and the life.
And he who believes in me will never die
Not you'll die and eventually you'll come back to life
Yeah, right so Lazarus is not really, you know Lazarus in his much. He's in is he's in Christ is not dead
Right, that's what he's telling her. Yeah
And so I mean then like
One of the conclusions to that is that
What sanctifies a church temple?
relics is therefore a testimony to the resurrection of the dead because we're
you know the church temple you know our own sort of local instantiation to the tabernacle right
becomes what it is because you have the presence of someone who whose body has become
the body of God the body of Christ. Right the space they occupy is holy space because they occupy it
the same way that
Moses had to take his shoes off next to the burning bush.
Yeah.
Wow.
So to wrap up this episode, we've been talking about the Tabernacle.
Where does it come from?
What is it patterned off of?
It's patterned off of the tent of God on the Holy Mountain,
Paradise, where he dwells with the sons of God,
those who are with him.
and we extended that out now in the...
the third half where we talked about how that applies now to the church within the New Testament,
within the period that we're now in. And one of the things that Father Stephen mentioned here at
the end was is that Christianity is not defined in the ancient world in terms of being simply a
list of beliefs. There are beliefs, for sure, right? There are beliefs. But I think that as modern
people, we tend to think of belief and here I am.
saying think of belief, right?
So I'm expressing the language
with this modern way of thinking.
We are modern people.
We tend to think of belief as the thing
that makes you really a Christian
or that makes you really whatever it is you are.
Like if you believe it truly, you know.
And so, I mean, one of the experiences that I've had,
you know, in ministry in the church
is that a lot of times people have,
a crisis or struggle within themselves.
Do I believe hard enough?
Do I trust hard enough?
Right?
Can I really forgive that person?
And by that they mean become convinced in my mind, not
to what they did doesn't matter, right?
Or something like that.
And so it becomes this kind of mental thing, right?
Which I mean, it's understandable.
Because that's what defines so much of our modern world.
I get it.
I understand why people feel that way.
What?
they think that way, right? But in Christianity traditionally and in Orthodox Christianity,
the question is not, do I believe hard enough or do I think the right things or do I have
the right opinions, but am I faithful? Am I practicing this faith, right? It's based on
what you do. There is Christian doctrine. There is Christian worldview, but it's based
on what you do. It's not the other way around. We tend in our time to think...
I need to be convinced of something and therefore I will act in the basis of that.
But Christianity is actually, it goes the other way.
It goes the other way that what we believe is based on what we do.
Now often in the modern world we need to explain things to help people engage in faithfulness,
right?
The whole point of catacletes is to teach people how to be faithful, to show them how to
be faithful. Right?
But it's not about trying to convince them that certain things are true so that then they can make the decision to be faithful.
If you come to the church to be baptized, you are convinced already.
So the question of Catechese is, is, is how do you be faithful?
And you know, connect to this, then of course, there's a very famous line, James chapter two verse 18,
we're seeing James is talking about this, this relationship between faith and works.
And if we understand faith, really as faithfulness, then this makes more sense.
He says this.
But someone will say, you have faith and I have works.
Show me your faith apart from your works and I will show you my faith by my works.
In other words, he's saying that faithfulness, real faith, is about what you do.
It's about what you do.
That there is no, they cannot be, you know, they don't exist apart.
They're not separated.
So how does this relate to what we've said about sacred space?
The tabernacle, the church, as related to the tabernacle.
You know, an ancient Israelite knows what he's supposed to do in the regards to the tabernacle.
It's all very clearly laid out for him, right, in the Scriptures.
It's been taught to him.
He knows what he's supposed to do.
God has said it to him.
God told him that through Moses, right?
We as Christians have received the teaching for what we are supposed to do.
We know what we need to do to be faithful.
We need to be engaged in the worship of God in our local
instantiation of the tabernacle, that is to say our parish church.
But it's not just in that place, it's also as it extends into our homes as well,
with prayer at home, with all of these things going on so that the home itself
becomes an extension of the church, that the church is expressed in the home.
You know, sometimes you'll all say things like
Well, you know, I can worship God on my own or you know that kind of thing. It's like well
It's what you're saying is somewhat true, right? It's not that you
You cannot talk to God in any place. You can talk to God in any place
But we also know that he said
Do this as my remembrance and he showed us how to do the Eucharist
He did not say here's one option
For how you could maybe worship me, you know
If you're feeling traditional, right, doesn't say that.
He says, do this.
There's a lot of very clear commandments.
And it says in scripture, if you love me,
you'll keep my commandments.
Not if you love me, you can pick which commandments
of mine you like, emphasize those.
And that'll be fine.
He says, if you love me, you keep my commandments.
That's stated many times in scripture in various ways,
many, many times, right?
And so, you know, in ancient Israel,
they're traveling with a tabernacle,
they're setting it up, they camp around it.
It's the Bruce.
center of their life if some ancient Israelites said, you know what?
I don't need to go to the tabernacle.
I don't need to offer the sacrifices.
I don't need to do these things.
Even if I've sinned, I don't have to do that stuff.
Because, you know, I can worship God in my own way.
No, you cannot.
Does that mean you can't pray in his own tent?
Of course, he can pray in his own tent.
Of course, but he's also been given very specific commandments from God as to
the tabernacle and how to relate to it.
Just as we have been given specific commandments by God.
with regards to the church, how to relate to it, what we're supposed to do.
This is what the tradition of the church is about.
Is about these acts of faithfulness.
And so I think one of the great values and understanding what the tabernacle is about
and how our church is now the tabernacle is that it gives us something very clear
to look at and say, this is what I needed to do.
This is what it means to be a faithful Christian, not just my Christian identity,
how I think of myself as a Christian.
but a faithful Christian.
Because an unfaithful Christian is not a Christian, not real.
Right? It's those who are faithful who are truly in Christ.
And faithfulness is something that we can see clearly and latch on to and
understand that we're doing it without a lot of psychological guessing
games. We don't need to do that. We just, are you doing the things?
Here's what the things are.
And even if you don't, it's Father Steven,
so even if you don't have the correct opinion
about every piece of theology,
because I mean, we don't, we all don't.
That's not what makes you faithful.
Now, if you latch on to an incorrect opinion
and really pursue it and step away from the church's
result of that, that is what heresy is.
And that's why it's a problem.
But the point is to be faithful.
And this is why even small children can be faithful.
This is why people without theological degrees
can be faithful.
You know, this is why faithfulness is possible for every-
single human person. And so I, this is a, to me, is a profound lens through which to understand the
Christian life and, and something that, that even people without a lot of theological education,
even people without interest in listening to weird, you know, Bible podcasts like this one
can still connect with and still do the things, you know, even if they are
theologically ignorant or whatever it might be.
So Father Stephen.
So as we talked about with the whole issue between the tabernacle and the temple
There's a strong
theme throughout the scriptures not just in the Old Testament because St. Peter continues into the New Testament
That the people of God those who are seeking to
be faithful to God to follow Christ
can't do that by settling in.
in this world or any of its cultures,
or any of its places at any time.
We've mostly lost sight of that in the modern world.
Other than our persecuted brothers and sisters in Christ
who are living under situations of persecution,
those of us probably most of the people listening
to this since we broadcast in English,
are living in places that are not that.
We're living in places where we've been allowed to and allowed ourselves to become very comfortable and very settled.
And we make a lot of excuses for this. We'll say, well, I'm in a culture that's, you know, a Christian culture, or at least historically was deeply influenced by Christianity.
Well, you know, ancient Israel was a Yahweh's culture. Ancient Judah was a Yahweh's culture.
When Christ came and lived and was killed, and Saint John the
Four Runner came and lived and was killed, was a culture that was
worshiping Yahweh the God of Israel. That doesn't give you the
license to settle down. That doesn't mean that the culture, the
society, the people and their will is on the right track, just
because they profess or identify themselves as being of the
of the truth.
religion in some sense. And we see this most of all in the fact that there's at least
at present and things can change very quickly, but at least at present there's not a lot of
risk of us becoming martyrs very low. And in fact we spend a lot of our time at a lot
of our effort in these societies.
trying to prevent ourselves from suffering any kind of even vague
persecution
as as Christians for Christianity for our Christian pay
Here's the problem I've said this once before in sort of a final thought
But if if Christianity isn't revolutionary then it's nothing
Anything that we call Christianity that fits very neatly in
into this world at any point in time in any place is not real Christianity.
If there's a political party in your country that you fit into very neatly, there's a problem
with your ideology.
If there's a cultural movement that you fit into very neatly, there's a problem with
your ideology.
you're able to go about your daily life.
your work life, your school life, and you go about it in the same way that your atheist
or other religion co-workers do. There's a problem with how you're living your work
life or your school life. Now this isn't to say that our goal as Christian should be
to go around and offend people, right? That's easy. Talk is cheap so we can go around and
say rude things.
judgmental things and go around and condemn people and get them to hate us and then pat ourselves on the back and say,
ah, see I'm being persecuted for the sake of Christ, right? I'm doing it right.
That's not what I'm getting at because that's not what the martyrs did. That's not what Christ did.
That's not what the prophets did. What they did was they lived a way of life,
that way of life that is now real Christianity.
They lived a way of life that was so radically out of step
With what the world values what it sees as good
What it sees as productive
What those in power wanted them to live so radically out of step
that
Those powers of the world wanted them dead wanted them destroyed one of them wanted wanted them stopped
This happened with the prophet Elijah, this happened with the prophet Elijah, this happened with the prophet Elijah.
Prophet Jeremiah pretty much everyone we talked about in this episode. This happened with.
And so this isn't something that begins by us imagining a perfect Christian society,
because just like the temple, we aren't given a blueprint for that in the scriptures.
We really aren't. That's not what the Torah is, by the way. We're not given a blueprint for this is
what society is. And so I'm going to go out and try and force it to be that. What we're given a
The blueprint for is what each of our lives.
should look like. And so it starts with each of us, it starts with me for me. It starts
with me calling myself to repentance, me finding the places where I'm very comfortable, where
I see things pretty much the same way non-Christians do looking at the same thing. The places where
I've been formed by my time and place and culture and not by Christ and finding those
and repenting of them myself.
And repenting.
not by changing my mind, changing my opinion, but by, as we've been saying, by changing how I live,
changing how I talk, changing how I act toward others, changing how I present myself,
changing all of those things about myself, and bringing them into line with Christ and who he is,
and how he lives. And the promise that we have in Scripture
Okay.
Yes.
is that if we get serious about that and we start doing that,
that's when people will really start to hate us.
And not just people out in the world,
not just, oh, you know, the angry atheist on the internet.
No, that's when other people in the Christian church
are gonna start hating us.
That's when everyone is going to start hating us.
Because Christ has promised that because
that's how the prophets were treated before us.
That's it.
he was treated as a servant is not greater than his master.
And so this is the mark of real Christianity when we're actually living it.
Real Christianity, when we're actually living it, means living it away that is not designed
to give offense to anyone, but that anyone who is in and of the world is going to find
deeply offensive.
their life in a way where we don't judge anyone.
but just the way we live, those people who are not following Christ feel judged by it.
That's the mark of a real Christian. That's what marked out when we read the lives of the saints
and the martyrs. That's what we see.
And so, when we remember them, when we talk about them tonight,
tonight when we talk about what this kind of holiness means and what God wants us to learn.
from having his meeting place be in a tent and not a permanent building.
It means that we need to live in a way that this world is not our home.
We don't fit in, not because we're trying not to fit in,
but because we're following Christ so intently that we don't notice how far out of step we are
with those who aren't.
Well, that is our show for today.
Thank you very much, everyone, for listening.
If you didn't get a chance to call in during a
previous live broadcast. This one was not live. We would still love to hear from you.
Either via email at Lord of Spirits at ancient faith.com. You can message us also at our Lord of Spirits
podcast, Facebook page. I read everything. Father Steven skims some things. But we can't respond
everything. We do respond once in a while. But we do save a lot of it for possible use in future
episodes. And join us for our live broadcast on the second and fourth Thursdays of most months
at 7 p.m. Eastern 4 p.m. Pacific.
Yeah, because in March.
We're not going to be doing our episodes live.
And the reason is-
Paul Memorex.
Yeah, it's going to all be Memorex in March 2022
and that's because of liturgical reasons.
The first time it'll be the first week of Lent,
we have to be in church.
And the second time it's going to be the eve
of the great feast of the Annunciation
on the calendar of that, both Father Stephen and I follow.
So, though, we will still have episodes on those nights,
but they are going to be pre-recorded.
So if you are on Facebook, though,
you can like our
join our discussion group, leave reviews, ratings everywhere, but most importantly,
please share this show with a friend whom you know is going to love it.
But don't be on Facebook if you don't have to.
And finally, be sure to go to www.agstrafate.com.strowksupport
and help make sure we and lots of other AFR podcasters stay on the air.
Thank you very much, good night, and God bless you and may you have a very good life.
You've been listening to The Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests,
Father Andrew Stephen Dam-
and Father Stephen DeYoung, a listener-supported presentation
of ancient faith radio.
And I beheld, and I heard the voice of many angels
round about the throne and the beasts and the elders,
and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000
and thousands of thousands,
saying with a loud voice, worthy is the land
that was slain to receive power and riches and wisdom
and strength and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5
versus 11 through 12.